<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hic et ubique, or, The humors of Dublin a comedy, acted privately, with general applause / written by Richard Head, Gent.</title>
            <author>Head, Richard, 1637?-1686?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15208</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12005954</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12005954</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43160)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52317)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 565:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hic et ubique, or, The humors of Dublin a comedy, acted privately, with general applause / written by Richard Head, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Head, Richard, 1637?-1686?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.D. for the Author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52317:1"/>
            <p>Hic et Ubique; OR, THE HUMORS OF DUBLIN. A COMEDY.</p>
            <p>Acted privately, with general Applauſe.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Richard Head,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Facilius eſt Carpere quàm Imitare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. D.</hi> for the Author. 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:52317:2"/>
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Momus.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Momus</speaker>
               <p>HA, ha, we're like to have a goodly Play y faith when our Author ſwore juſt now he knew not whether <hi>Pegaſus</hi> were Horſe or Cow, if a be no Poet, I wonder the Devil how he came to be ſo poor; for I've heard ſome ſay, Poverty and Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are inſeparable companions, but now I think on't, his fancie creeps in proſe, and ſometimes cuts a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or two in verſe, according as a was inſpir'd by <hi>Bacchus</hi>—but that he could not purchaſe alwayes,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And that's the reaſon that there's here ſuch lack.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of wit, ſince there was want of ſparkling Sack.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>What can you then expect but the dreggs of Ale? the beſt title you can give him is but a red lettice ſcribler, whoſe rimes and the ſpiggot keep time together.</p>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Muſoph.</hi>
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Muſophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Courteous ſpectators —</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
               <p>Save your ſelf the lobour, I have ſpoke the <hi>Prologue</hi> already.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Muſoph.</speaker>
               <p>Who ſent thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
               <p>My friends, Envy and Prejudice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Muſoph.</speaker>
               <p>Thy commiſſion's falſe, get hence, thy breath infects the aire, and wu'd be contagious here, but that the ſerenity of each face I view becom's it 's antidote. Avant.</p>
               <stage>(<hi>Exit Mome</hi>)</stage>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:52317:3"/>
                  <head>The Prologue.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our Author wrote this Play, but cannot tell</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whether or no his genius has done well.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mark well then what hee'l ſay, and doubtleſs you</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Will ſwear though't be not quaint, yet moſt is true.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heres no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian ſtories, nor ſuch things,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As ſome men fain, that flye upon the wings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of fancy only, and include the ſtation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of their own projects in imagination.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Experience dictates what we have to ſay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She being guide, I marvel who can ſtray.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hear't out with patience, for we'l all contend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To pleaſe you all, and not a Mome offend.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:52317:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>Drammatis Perſonae.</head>
               <item>ALderman <hi>Thrive-well</hi> Vintner in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Kil-tory.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quondam</hi> Citizens of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hope-well.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bank-rupt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Contriver.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tru<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phantaſtick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hic-et-nbique.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peregrine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scrivener.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Patrick. Kil-tory's</hi> man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Recipe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drawer.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Women.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caſſandra, Thrive-wels</hi> daughter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jane</hi> her maid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Contrivers</hi> Wife.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hope-wells</hi> Wife.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sue-Pouch</hi> a Land-Lady.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scene</hi> Dublin.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52317:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 1. <hi>Scene</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Peregrine,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hopewell, Contriver, Truſt-all, Bankrupt, Phantaſtick, Hic &amp; ubique.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, welcome aſhore.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hopewel.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks, noble Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregrine.</speaker>
                     <p>The like to you all, Gentlemen. What, melancholly, Mr. <hi>Truſtall?</hi> Come, come, though y'are altogether a ſtranger in this Countrey, yet let not your unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance therewith too much diſcompoſe your ſpirits, or diſturb your reſt: y'are remov'd but two degrees from your native habitation, and there's but little difference between the Climates. The generality of <hi>Dublin</hi>'s Inhabitants may juſtly boaſt of as great a meaſure of civility as the greateſt pretenders thereunto elſewhere; only their loſſes and croſſes has ſo refin'd their wits, that they are become the beſt oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick Polititians.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, 'tis not ſo much the remembrance of my native ſoil, as the loſſe of a fair promiſing fortune; together with the leaving behind me my dear Wife and Children, that thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe me, leaving my diſſipated thoughts in a continued ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tafie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>The conſideration hereof would diſſwade the moſt cenſorious from blaming your dejection. However, be of good comfort, though the world has faln out with you, I wu'd not have you therefore be revenged on your ſelf, or take pet, and be miſerable in ſpight.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52317:5"/>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I am ſenſible that I merit blame, but not the leaſt pitty; ſince my ſufferings are the ſole effect of my overmuch (fooliſh) credulity, occaſioned by my greedineſs of trade: graſping at every motion of credit, I thought to oblige and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>Never to come neer you after.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Woful experience inform'd me ſo, for now do I find their names in my debt books, meerly as ſo many <hi>memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dums</hi> of my folly, never to be cancel'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Hang all ſad thoughts, extaſies, and diſtracting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances (ſay I) let's drink a glaſs of Sack and drown 'em all therein. Since we know none that will give us our welcome to <hi>Ireland,</hi> lets e'ne do't our ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Well ſaid, faith Boy, let's away then to the next Tavern. Here's money lads, and bills of Exchange too, which wee'l exchange for Sack: We cannot want, for when we have ſpent all our Engliſh moneys, here's Spaniſh and French, more than theſe Ram-creſted Citizens know what to do withal. It ſhall go hard but our wits ſhall put in for a half ſhare among 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Now Sir, I have time to thank you, for your ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility aboard; truly I knew not what to have done without you; you ſtood to me in my weakneſſe, we women are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome ſickly things at Sea. <stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewel.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Save you Gentlemen. Came ye out of <hi>England?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>The Sun has not run ſix minutes, thirteen ſeconds ſince we landed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray Sir, what Country man are you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I've been ſo long a Traveller, I don't juſtly know.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>And it may be not very well underſtand what you ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye make of me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>By your language, you ſeem a rabbinical Chriſtian; by your geſture, an Aegyptian-French Magician.</p>
                     <p>But I pray Gentlemen, what news at <hi>London?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>My gaul hath overflown its banks, and ſo irritated my animoſity againſt your diſſimilar abjurgating ſimilitudes, that I am loth to give your pluſh Jacket any other than bruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfaction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52317:5"/>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>If you do, pray Sir let it be in Engliſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Novelties (you would ſay) according to Courtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, or novel as the French has it, but news according to the Vulgar. Some there is though not much, let me ſee this is <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> or as the great <hi>Mogol</hi> calls it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>If this be your way of telling news, I ſhall ſooner hear thereof from my friends at <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I'le condeſcend then to the imbecility of your veterane capacity. A Saturday night laſt, I ſup'd with <hi>Dick-Shallow</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> (for he and I are ſo intimately acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that we are never aſunder.) A Monday night I came to <hi>Holly-head,</hi> where I found theſe Gent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>The expedition of your journey ſeems to me very ſtrange Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>You wou'd not think ſo, had you but ſeen me fly through the air. I tell you my horſe is ſo extream ſwift in his motion, that winged <hi>Pegaſus</hi> is but a dull Aſſe to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>I wou'd I cu'd ſee this wonderful ſwift Animal.</p>
                     <p>Have you brought him o're with you Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>D'ye think that my brain-pan inſtead of guts, is ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified with obfuſcoſities? though I venture him at land, I'de not hazard ſuch a treaſure at Sea.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>This is a long parentheſis. You were about to tell the Gentleman ſome news.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>'Slife tis right; why, then to be ſhort, <hi>London's Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>That's without doubt; but have you no ſtranger news to relate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Have but patience, and I ſhall gradually inform your curioſity. Firſt then, Houſes and Shops are ſo dear in <hi>London,</hi> that ſome Shopkeepers are forc'd to ſell their wares in the Country.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I believe ſo, and their wearing cloaths too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>The Mercers and Bookſellers are deeply in law about the Fee-ſimple of <hi>Ludgate,</hi> O 'tis diſputable which ſhall carry it. As for <hi>Newgate</hi> that's to be let.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo it may ſtand, for I know not who wou'd wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly take it, but thy grounds for this conceit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, the doors were faſt lockt up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52317:6"/>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I wonder how thou got'ſt out then, unleſſe thou haſt a body as penetrating as a ſpirit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>And I ſaw a bill upon 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>That may be, a Doctors pocky bill, or a pocky Doctors bill; why, art thou ſo ignorant, to be guilty of ſo groſs a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art as blind as a Polebeg Oiſter, not to ſee a well digeſted conceit of mine therein. But to proceed: younger Brothers never rackt their wits and inventions ſo much as now, to ſupply their neceſſary expence. The Ladies are grown ſo inſatiate, as that they are not content without ſeven or eight baudy Pentioners, whereby they can hardly purchaſe provocatives enough to render 'em capable of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Stallion. Falſe Dice wo'nt avail neither, for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil has taught even the Phanatick to be a Gameſter. The Sea and the Pox has ſwept away one half of the Cock-neighs, and the other half expect to end their daies by hanging like plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets to a line, and are in hopes when wound up, to go to Heaven by Clockwork.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>What an aſſe was I, that I could not think of this; well, ſince 'tis not my invention, I'le go and acquaint all the Grave-makers in the Town, that there's one has brought in an innovation, which may prove deſtructive to their profeſſion; for which I hope they'l immediately digg him a grave, ſhall at leaſt reach to the <hi>Anti-podes.</hi>
                        <stage>(aſide.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Breaking</hi>'s now <hi>a la mode,</hi> and that makes this ſon of a Coſtermonger in the faſhion: (to <hi>Contriver</hi>) add to him <hi>Bankrupt</hi> and <hi>Truſtall,</hi> and they'l make a leaſh of Knights of the burning Peſtle, that are come into the Weſtern parts for ſtrange adventures. This here is coutriving to drein St. <hi>George</hi>'s Channel, being ſo dangerous to ſea-men in Winter time, and when 'tis done, he is to have a Patent for the ſole tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Boggs and Laughs of Iriſh growth into forreign parts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>But Sir, y'ave loſt the main ſubject of your diſcourſe <hi>viz.</hi> the famous and now moſt glorious City, <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>No ſuch matter; there are Cities in <hi>Terra incognita</hi> that I have ſeen nay and been drunk in, (there I lie, for now I remember my ſelf, they drink nothing there but Coffee and Chocolate.)</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52317:6"/>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>But what of them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay that they for Architecture do as much excel <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> as my horſe that I told you of, is to be prefer'd before a gelding of fifty pound price.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>You are a Traveller I perceive then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I am ſo, 'tis novelty I ſolely take delight in, which makes me no where a conſtant reſident.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank:</speaker>
                     <p>I believe ſo, for he will ſtay in no place longer than he can be truſted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak once more, and down goes thy brazen head. No Sir, my aim therein was to learn diverſity of languages, that thereby I might at will pick-lock the treaſury of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therein contained: and out of the manners of each na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, extract ſomewhat excellent for my peculiar obſervation and imitation: what progreſſe I have made herein, let my carriage and language expreſſe it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>Travel I confeſſe in joys ſo many worthy priviledges, that the hazard and labour that accompanies it, ſhould not in the leaſt deterr us from it: for we are not ſo to indulge the body, as to ſtarve the underſtanding. This is the ready was to improve an imature judgment. But inſtead hereof, ſome after a vaſt expence, return at length only metamorphoſed from Engliſh Aſſes, to French Apes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Enough, enough Sir, let's go to the Tavern. The knowledge that this Gentleman has of the City, will inform us where's the beſt wine. Come old Sir <hi>John,</hi> you'l favour us with your company.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>What Tavern d'ye pitch on? the <hi>London</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, we have had too much to do with <hi>London</hi> Taverns already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then, the Feathers.
<stage>(Exeunt.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52317:7"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 1. <hi>Scene</hi> 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Collonel <hi>Kil-tory</hi> and <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>KIlto.</speaker>
                     <p>Once more (my fair <hi>Caſſandra</hi>) the bleſt ſates have breath'd upon my hopes, and blown thoſe ſparks into a blazing flame, which lay conceal'd in the dark embers of your life-extinguiſhing abſence, now I find the ſun-ſhine of your preſence, thawing the congeal'd icineſſe of my heart, and makes it ſpread like the Marigold, tending it's courſe to your motion. Faireſt (and moſt worthy of that epithite of all your ſex) be not cruel to me, becauſe nature has been kind to you: let not your beautif<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l prerogative tyraunize, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let it's ſweet influence be communicative. What ſay you Lady, can you love?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>As yet I know not how to anſwer you, men are prone to promiſe that in the height of their amorous ſancies, which they ne'er intend to perform: and we poor ſilly eredulous maidens are too too oft caught with ſuch alluring bates of fair promiſing pretences, I know not why you ſhould deſire me not to be cruel, when 'tis the proper nature of your whole ſex to be guilty thereof: otherwiſe, you wou'd not thus continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally beleaguer us, and if you cannot obtain a fair ſurrender, you'l attempt the ſtorming of our maiden Caſtles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilto.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, let me be exempted out of that number, ſince my only battery ſhall be loving Artillery, perſwaſive argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. There ſhall be no Soldiers liſted under my command, whoſe ſtrength or policy you may fear in the leaſt, as diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, flattery, equivocation, falſe oaths, mutual enemies to us both. My deſires are honeſt, my intentions reall, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts legal, what then ſhou'd hinder the crowning of our loves?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Soft Sir, let not your confident hopes o're run your reaſon and diſcretion, y'are in my opinion too hot upon the onſet, and ſuch commonly come off with the loſſe of one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52317:7"/>or other. Be adviſed therefore, and let time which tries all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, try alſo the reality of your affection, to whoſe teſt let me leave you for a while.
<stage>(Exit.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilto.</speaker>
                     <p>Delays to me are but ſlat denials: a long grace ſuits not with a ſharp ſtomack: It's their ſubtilty thus to hold us in ſuſpence, the more to inflame our deſires. Methinks I could now as willingly hate every part of her ſex, as formerly I lov'd she whole for her ſake, but that I am partly aſſur'd my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's a woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Moiſtere, here is one beating de dore, wou'd make ſpeak for dy ſhelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilto.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet I cannot but love her, her ſweet Idea is too deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted in my heart, ſo eaſily to be pul'd out; never did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cies behold a fairer object, ſhee's now the ſole and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſubject of my cogitations.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>O yea, between me and God achree, my Moiſtare will make mad for my ſhelf. Upjack and ſupjack; <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hoo fuato de Deole ale thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilto.</speaker>
                     <p>No I muſt ſmother the ripe ſallies of my inflam'd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, and ſtudy what it is to be mart again, and how much theſe admired pieces of imperfection fall ſhort of his merit. Whilſt I was ſcouring the Mountains and skipping the Boggs, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the very ſpawn of rebellion, I had none of theſe qualms. I cu'd have then driven a ſcore or two of theſe white cloven Devils, without pity or regard. But ſince Mrs. <hi>Peace</hi> came ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with us, ſhe has perſwaded us to change our Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece for a ſoft Pillow, the ground (covered with the ſpangled Canopy of Heaven) for a down-bed, and that's naught too without a wench. Great <hi>Mers</hi> aſſiſt me, and conjure this Devil love out of me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>By my Goſſops hand, and my Faders ſhaddle, <hi>Kilpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> will be muſh fear by and preſhently, to ſee my Moiſtare make conjuration. <hi>Arra Moiſtare</hi> by St. Sonday, 'cis ill kind for dy Faders ſhild, to be making ſpeech wit dy ſhelf, and no body, Be me fet and be, I do hate de De-vil, as I do <hi>Olivers</hi> ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jer, and if he come preſently, my ſhelf will run away. <hi>Arrahall.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilto.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Patrick.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Sha, ſha, <hi>tatuggemi Moiſtare.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilto.</speaker>
                     <p>What's the matter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Dere is one wu'd fain be ſpeaking for dee.
<stage>(<hi>Exeunt.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52317:8"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 1. <hi>Scene</hi> 3.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewell, Peregrine, Bankrupt, Contriver</hi> and <hi>Truſtall.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THrive.</speaker>
                     <p>And is it poſſible Sir, that you are old <hi>Peregrine's</hi> ſon, the Eaſt <hi>India</hi> Merchant? for your Fathers ſake (whoſe memory I honour) command me wherein I may be ſerviceable to you; let me requeſt you to be no ſtranger to my houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks is the leaſt I can render you Sir, for this great favour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>If my heart ſpeak not in my tongue, let my name be blaſted with perpetual ignominy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>What ever others ſpeak malevolently of fortune, I muſt proclaim her conſtant in her propitious ſmiles on me. Though I have travel'd from Pole to Pole, I ever found ſome civil, even among the barbarous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Bankrupt,</hi> ſure I ſhould know you Sir, I've been acquainted with the name, and not unlikely your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, my name is ſo common every where, that 'tis no great wonder if y'are miſtaken in the knowledge of me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trive.</speaker>
                     <p>But I ſhall eaſily convince you that I am not miſtaken by particularizing where you liv'd. Were not you a Colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Corn-bill, London?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Heaven grant a does not betray us.
<stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſſe I was ever a man of a good colour, and cu'd colour well what I did. But I know not your meaning Sir. Now had I rather been in St. <hi>Georges</hi> Channel in a great ſtorm, than to have met with this man.
<stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd I were employ'd by the King for the finding out <hi>Obrazeele</hi> to rid me of my preſent fears.
<stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir fear not that my knowledge of you, ſhall prove detrimental, but rather tend to your future ſecurity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I'me glad 'tis come to that, I was juſt at my wits end.
<stage>(aſide.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo was I too, I lik't him not at firſt ſight, 'a was ſo forward to be acquainted with us.
<stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Being then confident of your fidelity, I ſhall commit to your charge a ſecret.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52317:8"/>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Which you may be confident I ſhall keep ſafe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Trade failing, and my creditors too haſty to receive, what my debtors were too ſlow in paying me, I was neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to fly from perpetual impriſonment. All that the ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my departure wu'd permit me to take, I've brought hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; upon which ſlender baſis, I intend to raiſe the ſtructure of a future livelyhood, This Gent. Mr. <hi>Truſtall,</hi> is a fellow-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer with me in the ſame condition.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay Gentlemen, ſince ye have made Mr. <hi>Thrivewell</hi> your Confeſſor, 'a ſhall be mine too; I'le promiſe you Sir, I ſtay'd in <hi>London</hi> ſo long for my own pleaſure, that my Creditors had like to have made me ſtay a little longer for theirs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith Gentlemen, I ſuſpected no leſſe, though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon civility wu'd not permit me to vent my thoughts. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice at your eſcape, 'tis enough that you have your liberty; for 'tis ſuch an inſtrument that if you make good uſe on't, 'twil procure you a being any where; What think you of me? I was never brought up to any Trade, yet live handſomly; I confeſſe I was born to land, and enjoy'd it ſo long, till I was weary on't, and then was never at reſt, till out of that dirty lump, I had extracted a pure and portable <hi>Elixir.</hi> In ſhort, to free my ſelf from that trouble &amp; vexation that are the inſeperable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of Lands and Tenements, I ſold 'em.
<stage>(Caveat Emptor)</stage> The monies I have long ſince ſpent, yet want not; the Earth's large, and has enough, (and to ſpare) to ſupply the wants of all her induſtrious children. He that has wit, (I think needs no plow; the apprehenſion of which perſwades me, not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to any place. My great Grand-father <hi>Adam,</hi> (Emperor of the whole world) left me ſomething every where, and I find it truly paid me where e're I come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt needs crave your pardon for my abrupt leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, I have buſineſſe of concernment (which I had almoſt forgot) that requires me, and I hope we ſhall henceforth be no ſtrangers to each other,
<stage>(<hi>Exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>My Maſters, we have trifled away too much time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, 'twere very requiſite we redeem what's loſt, by making treble uſe of the preſent. Preferring employments will neither proffer nor proſtitute themſelves, unleſſe we court them with labour and expence; as for my part (according to the proverb) <hi>omnem lapidem movebo,</hi> not leave a ſtone unturned, 'till my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52317:9"/>by my endeavours are arrived at the Cape of good hope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Contriver,</hi> though you are as much a ſtranger to this Country as we, yet I look upon you to be better skilld in projecting: your advice therefore, what courſe were we beſt to take?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>As I'me a Gentleman, if you'l take my opinion with you, I'me clearly for the ſecond courſe, but believe me 'twere beſt for you to take ſome ſpeedy courſe, leſt e're long, a red Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring make up all the courſes in your dinner; if you'le conſult where's the beſt Sack, how to procuve a handſome Girl, and a good noiſe of Muſick, (they'r beſt together) I'le be of your counſel, otherwiſe I ſhall leave you to your worldly thoughts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you may be much deceived in your conceited happineſſe, though fortune hitherto has look'd ſmilingly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, don't therefore vainly imagine, that ſhe doats on you as her Minion. Woful experience has forc'd her chiefeſt favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites to confeſſe, that ſhe is <hi>nunquam ſtabilis,</hi> and by taking no more than ſhe gave, leaves 'em in a condition far more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than e're ſhe found 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>I value neither the ſtrumpets love nor hatred, I'me proof againſt the worſt ſhe can inflict on me; what e're it be, <hi>equo animo feram.</hi> Adverſity ſhall not depreſs me ſo low, as to make me forget what I was, nor proſperity exalt me ſo high, as to ſlight my friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt Sirs, let's provide us convenient lodgings, that done we may talk of our buſineſs at leaſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Let's about it then; but what's become of <hi>Phantaſtick, Hic &amp; ubique,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Hopewel?</hi> tha've given us the ſlip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>They deſir'd to be excus'd, being gone to procure Mrs. <hi>Hopewel</hi> a lodging.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>And I warrant you they intend to take up their quar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters with her; 'twas cunningly plotted.
<stage>(<hi>Exeunt.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52317:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 1. <hi>Scene</hi> 4.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Mrs. <hi>Hopewel ſola.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mris. Hope.</speaker>
                     <p>In a ſtrange Country! all ſtrangers too! no acquaintance! no kindred! four hundred miles from home, and a woman too! what condition is more uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table than mine? Alas! me thinks I cu'd take pleaſure in my tears, and with ſharp bluſtring ſighs, blow ſweetneſſe upon my ſorrows: But ſtay, I'le not grow deſperate, but recollect my thoughts, and play bad cards at the beſt advantage; I will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore aid from Heaven, and ſtudy how I may become a favorite to each Deity; pluck up my failing ſpirits, and preſerve my diſconſolate and deſpairing ſelf with comfortable hopes and expectations. Nature took pains in forming me beautiful, and age has not ſo much impair'd it, but that there's enough ſtill to attract both love and pity from any breſt that is amorous. Why may not I then follow the preſidents of thouſands of our ſex, that in the ebb of their proſperities, have angled with their wits (baited with their beauties) in the ſwift ſtreams of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whence they have drawn up large and rich fiſhes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breaking the honourable line of their reputation. That I am a Wife 'tis too certain, but here are none that know it; therefore will I conceal it, and act the part of a Widdow, yet never wrong my Husband. Time cannot but furniſh me with acquaintance, and when I find my ſelf courted by a perſon conſiderable, I'le meet his flames with pretended affections, ſo far as ſhall ſtrengthen his perſeverance, yet ſtill maintain the principle of my own integrity. Enter <hi>Phantaſtick</hi> and <hi>Hic &amp; ubique.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What my fellow Traveller? How is it now? what think you of <hi>Ireland?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hope.</speaker>
                     <p>In truth Sir, I know not, but I hope well ſtill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Gramercy wench, keep in that mind, and the more to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52317:10"/>encourage thee, thou ſhalt never want the benefit of man or money, whilſt I am furniſht with either.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hopew.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you, good Sir, I wiſh I may deſerve your kindneſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Want! by this hand ſhe ſhall not want; Lady, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe me here's money enough, and when this is ſpent, ne're fear but we'l have more; all which, and my ſelf, are at your ſervice, command either, or both together. I have the ſpirit of a Gentleman, and I muſt drink Sack.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hope.</speaker>
                     <p>By no means Sir, you have been too laviſh already, and this Gentleman likewiſe; I ſhall beg your pardon, tis time to repair to my lodging.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith then, Madam, we'l wait upon you thither.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I wud not loſe that honour, nor become guilty of ſo grand an abſurdity, as to neglect it, for the beſt Jewel in Queen <hi>Dido's</hi> Cabinet; no Madam, tis early yet, and before we mew up our ſelves in our lodgings, we'l take a walk, and recreate our ſelves with the various objects of the City; and as you view it, take notice of what you like beſt; I'le procure it— here's heavy Gold, and a light heart boys— ha—honeſt <hi>Hic,</hi> what ſaiſt thou to't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay, ſpend it all quickly, and then you'l have a light pocket too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou put'ſt me in the mind of a common ſaying here, that thoſe that come hither are not in a probability of thriving, til they have ſpent what Engliſh money they brought with them, if this be true, I'le make all the haſt I can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, rather than you ſhould be too much put to't, Ile help you, that you may the ſooner ſit down in the predicament of bettering your condition.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hopew.</speaker>
                     <p>You invent this diſcourſe, I conceive, only to make your ſelves merry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith we are the ſons of mirth and pleaſure; delight and handſom Ladies (ſuch as yourſelf) are the only Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones of our deſires. We adore no Deities but <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> Let the Uſurer fall down and worſhip his bags, groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the weight of 'em: Let the Soldier fight for honour till his forward limbs be drencht in blood, by the ſword of his conquering Enemie; Let the Schollar quarrel in Logical Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, pickt out of <hi>Ramus,</hi> till he break <hi>Priſcians</hi> head. Let
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52317:10"/>us drink Sack, which will make us conceit our ſelves to have that which they ſo ſtrenuouſly content for; to the obtaining of which let's loſe no time.
<stage>(<hi>Exeunt</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 1. <hi>Scene</hi> 5.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewell</hi> and <hi>Bankrupt.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THrivew.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Bankrupt,</hi> you are much miſtaken in your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of <hi>Dublin;</hi> by that time you have been here as long as I, you may experimentally know the contrary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>You have good cauſe to think the beſt on't, however Sir, as having gotten a good eſtate in't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>I may thank a good careful Wife for't; though I ſay't, ſhe's handſom too, and yet I dare ſay, honeſt withall. A merry Grig, to give Gueſts content. When I came over firſt, I knew not what to have done without her; for, by waiting a great while for a very beneficial employment, which I was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by this great man and 'tother, all my money was gone, then cu'd I not ſtoop to be a Drawer, that was ſo lately a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, at length my wife had taken a houſe unknown to me, and I know not how it came to paſs, got ſo much credit as to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it befitting lodgers. In a ſhort time all our rooms were fill'd with Gallants; and to accomodate them better, we kept a cup of very good Beer, as alſo a bottle of Wine. Then cu'd I ride abroad, and ſtay a month together, yet ſtill the trade went on at home; and ſuch a one it was, that it quickly rais'd me monies to purchaſe this Tavern I now live in, well furniſht with wine; but fortune's not alike favourable to all, according to that old ſaying.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non cuivis homini contingit adire corinthum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Few women make manifeſt by their lives, the intents of their creation, that is to be an help to man, and that's it makes me the more admire your wiſe. I've heard of many that have undone their Husbands, but few that prefers the welfare of 'em, before the indulging of their own luxurious (and often luſtfull) appetites. I cu'd wiſh my own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition did not prompt me to ſay what I do.</p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52317:11"/>
                     <p> I have a Wife ('twere well, if I never had any) who lives, I fear to be a continual thorn in my ſide. What I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd ſhe ſcatter'd; yet durſt not reprehend her for't, till 'twas palpably known, ſhe admitted others to her embraces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides my ſelf. Perceiving and fore-ſeeing my downfall, ſhe haſtens it by the taking what caſh ſhe cu'd, and left me to be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by my mercileſs creditors; had not ſudden flight (as I told you) prevented it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>I pitty your condition, and do wiſh I knew any way that might now be a ſupport unto you, for I aſſure you this is a place wherein 'tis no eaſie matter to borrow money, nay, or be truſted long for meat and drink; Proviſion indeed is cheap, becauſe money is ſcarce; yet good liquor is dear, 'cauſe there are ſo many that will pawn their cloaks, but thei'le have it; and much good may do 'em; for my part I ſhall ne're fear a ſcarecity thereof, ſince ther's almoſt as many Ale-houſes, as good fellowes; to be ſhort, thoſe that live heer, are all old Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and ſuch you know, fight cunningly. 'Tis a great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight me thinks in the Engliſh Gentry, in ſending their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into forreign parts, to learn wit and manners, whereas it were far more expedient to ſend 'em hither; for here they may ſo learn to live, as to live any where: And after ſeven years aboad in this country, they need never fear being troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the failing Sickneſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I doubt your diſcourſe ſavours more of wit, than truth. But how wu'd you adviſe me to ſecure my ſelf from my debts in <hi>London?</hi> As for protection, by reaſon of the many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes occaſion'd by 'em, they are cald in, I hear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>However fear not: Ther's a great Gulf man betwixt you, and your creditors.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>I but theſe letters of Atorney, I fear 'em more, than the lark does the hobby.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>You trouble your ſelf to no purpoſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>But is't not uſual for ſuch letters to be ſent over, the witneſſes being ſworn in Chancery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Such a thing may be, but then ther's a remedy; if e're it comes to that, repair to me, and I'le ſhew you the hole, that I my ſelfcrept through upon the like account.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52317:11"/>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>You have much eas'd me of my fears. But ſtill I'me in a labrynth of cares, how I ſhall live, ſince the currant of my money is but ſmall, and will ſoon be waſted, without ſome rivolets of ſupply. Well, I muſt pinch this carcaſs, as much as e're I pamper'd it. O <hi>London, London!</hi> The very naming thee doth diſturb me, and the fixing of my thoughts thereon, almoſt deſtracts me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed Mr. <hi>Bankrupt</hi> you'r too blame to complain, thus in vain; what can't be cur'd, muſt be indur'd. Be of good comfort. <hi>Dum ſpiro ſpero,</hi> you ſee as old as I am; I have not forgot all my latine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, your long abſence from that famous City, hath made you forget i'ts ſtately building, pleaſant walkes, with a hundred delighting places for paſtime; wherein all pleaſure is Epitomiz'd and contracted. How oft have I there plung'd over head and ears in all ſorts of delight, feaſting my ſenſes with thoſe things, that are moſt ſuitable to each! But I'le ne're think on thoſe dayes, ſince I never expect to enjoy the like.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Bravely reſolv'd, and to begin, I think you were beſt to diſpoſe of thoſe fine Cloaths, that ſaw ſome of thoſe fine dayes, leſt they ſhu'd put you in mind on 'em again; thei'le you two or three good Bandle ſuites, with laſting Woolen ſtockings, which will be much more convenient for this Country weeping weather, you muſt expect to find here little, other than rany or windy, and the reaſon is according to ſome Rabbyes opinions, becauſe the windy God <hi>Aeolus,</hi> and <hi>phlegmatick Luna</hi> are in contention, whither the one ſhall make it his Court, or the other her piſpot. The natives yeild ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the God, for which the goddeſs puniſht 'em with an hereditary diſeaſe, called the fundamental thorow-goe-nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I'me ſure I have been troubled with it four or five dayes— your pardon—your pardon Sir
<stage>(<hi>Exit</hi> as untruſſing)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>If his Wife were to look for him now, ſhe might quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find him out by the ſcent
<stage>(<hi>Exit</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52317:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 1. <hi>Scene</hi> 6.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Caſſandra ſola.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CAſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Whither ſhall I fly for refuge? what Sanctuary can protect me from this purſuing ſhadow, which like ſome ill <hi>Genius</hi> ſtill follows me, I fear, to the utter ruine of my reſt? My antipathy againſt him is ſo ſtrong, that rather than admit of his love, I cu'd be content to court ſome hedge-born ſlave, whoſe raggs and rudeneſs render him a fit companion for ſwine and dunghils. And yet I know not why, love ſeldome gives a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for what a does. Methinks his embraces are like the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cling of Snakes, his voice like the howling of a Wolf, and his ſmiles like the grinning of a Monkey.
<stage>(Enter <hi>Kiltory.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Well overtaken Lady. (<hi>ſhe offers to go</hi>) Nay, be not ſo hard harted as to leave me thus, who loves you dearly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray forbear Sir, the bias of my thoughts run other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies; therefore give me leave to enjoy the benefit of my freedom, which ſhu'd I looſe (but as yet it lies in my power to preſerve) I ſhu'd account my ſelf moſt miſerable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall not looſe, but enlarge it; for you ſhall enjoy a man, the bounty of whoſe affections ſhall dayly multiply your happineſs. I'le be your Guardian, and defend you from every ſtorm of aproaching injury.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My fears—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>What?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing, if you and love ne're come near me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Wu'd you be ſo uncharitable as to live in hate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>No, by my Virgin-whiteneſs, I've charity for all men; but was never yet fond enough to give away my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis common to your ſex.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>And may be proper for me hereafter, but as yet I could never ſee that man I cu'd love ſo well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Is there no hopes for me then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly Sir, I think none.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52317:12"/>
                     <speaker>Kiltor.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then did you give me hopes, when you told me you wu'd leave me to the teſt of time?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>That was but to ſtop your importunity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>How long will you leave me to that re<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>For ever.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Say you ſo? — This is not the way (<hi>aſide</hi>) — come Lady, I will —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Do what Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Make you my Bride.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>But I ſay, you ſhall never.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>And to begin I muſt —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Muſt what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Kiſſe you, Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray forbear Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Introath I muſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly you muſt not, (<hi>kiſſes her</hi>) fie Sir, I was never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſuch rudeneſſe and rumbling before—If you'l not be civil, Ile cry out, and make your credit ſuſpected. Pray Sir believe me, I ſwear I cannot love you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>I do — and know I am not ſuch a fool, to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate in love with a Statue: I value not your diſdain; and do not think your immaginary beauty is able to make me pule, whine, and exclaim againſt Heaven. Alas, you have no Virtue, but what mans fond conceit and feigned praiſes inveſts you withall; I confeſſe y'ave all ſubtilty enough, by which you maintain and keep up your good eſtimation among men: The height of your wiſdom conſiſts in <hi>I,</hi> and <hi>No,</hi> and you muſt be accounted ſolid and prudent, though you cannot ſpeak three words of ſenſe, provided y'ave obtained the gift of Silence; and you muſt be continent by all means too, becauſe y'ave the Art of concealing your deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſo temperate, as if your bodies required not eating; forbearing in the preſence of men, whetting your ſtomacks upon their appetites, to feed <hi>Cormorant</hi>-like in private. Wine is inflaming, and flies up into the face; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y'are only for ſips, till you come among your Goſ-ſips, and then you can drink pottle after pottle, with a ſmall Cawdle or two, that contain gallons a piece; and being elevated, you talk of things that do'nt concern ye: Having overgorg'd your ſelves, you pretend you are not well, and ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52317:13"/>go to bed. Laſtly, ſo cleanly, that you wu'd perſwade us you evacuate no excrements.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I can endure no longer: farewell Sir, this diſcourſe wu'd have better ſuited with a Bear-garden, exclaiming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome Apple-woman for not ſelling twelve a penny.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! have I toucht your Copy-hold? now am I ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently reveng'd; I muſt ſtudy to forget her: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I have ſo much inveigh'd againſt her ſex, my heart ſpake otherwiſe; queſtionleſſe Woman is a moſt divine Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therefore worthily deſerves to be beloved: but Ile reſt a while,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil Experience tels me I have found</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One free to love, and is with beauty crown'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Patrick</hi> crying.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Fuillilaloo!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kiltor.</speaker>
                     <p>How now Sirrah?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patrick.</speaker>
                     <p>The donny fellow make buſe for my Moiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>What Fellow?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patrick.</speaker>
                     <p>He was no Sougare nor Musketteer, but a greyſhy guddy hang of a Peek-man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>And what of him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Fuy by St. <hi>Patrick</hi> agra, he put de ſuckation upon my weef. I will tell dee tale if thou wilt Gluntamee. I came in wid my piſhfork upon my back, thou know'ſt, and I ſee a greyſhy guddy hang upon my weef, and I did creep in like a michear, to the wattles upon de loft abow thou know'ſt, and there I did ſee putting the great ſuck upon my weef, as if thy own ſhelf was there Moiſter; and becauſe I wu'd make haſte, I fell down upon 'em, and leek to have more than half break my neck; then wid my piſhfork I clap him upon de Narſum, and I did make ſharge for him in the Kings name, thou know'ſt, to ſtay dere til I fetch the Cunt—ſtable; but before I came, this chverech craveRauge make run away for himſhelf: and looky there Moiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why what wudſt have me doo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Fea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>een take my weef to thine own ſhelf, for <hi>Patrick</hi> will not lie with his weef <hi>Shuane</hi> again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why wudſt a have me lie with her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea feat if thou wilt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52317:13"/>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Sir, 'tis ſo great a favour, I ſhall never be able to make your brogues a requital. However take this
<stage>(<hi>kicks him</hi>)</stage> in part of ſatisfaction; nay, this
<stage>(<hi>kicks him again</hi>)</stage> too, that I may come out of your debt the ſooner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>Finis Actus Primi.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 2. <hi>Scene</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Phantaſtick, Hie &amp; uhique,</hi> and <hi>Sue Pouch.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>REally y'are the prittieſt, ſweeteſt natur'd Gent. and the merrieſt Gueſt, that ever I entertain'd in my life, and I am ſure I have been an houſe-keeper this ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years, come <hi>Candlemas.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith Landlady, 'tis my cuſtom to be merry where ere I come. I muſt be like my ſelf, noble and generous. I can as well be hang'd as degenerate from a Gentleman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Hang all baſe pinching Miſers, greedy Earth-worms, that place all their delight in melancholly poſſeſſing, not merrily ſpending, and emptying their full cram'd bags.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let 'em rot with their cares,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And worldly affairs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And worm-eat their ſouls with their treaſures</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thoſe only live brave,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That ſpend what they have,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſpin out their lives in their pleaſures.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore we will ſhape</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our Deſigns for the Grape,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where Fancy is feather'd with freedom;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our ſouls do diſdain</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The world with its gain,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Give Riches to ſlaves that ſhall need'em.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52317:14"/>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Gramarcy <hi>Hic:</hi> the lines are indifferent, and wud ſound better, were not that throat of thine ſo much like the baſe of a <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Horn-pipe, whilſt thy Treble runs Diviſions like a Ram in a halter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha, that was a wittie one; y'are an arch Wag, Ile warrant you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>If you mean an arch Wag-tail, y'ave hit the nail oth'head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>But Landlady, they ſay y'are well read.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo the report goes of thee, but tis in two-leav'd books.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not how well I'm read, but I have read much.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>What Authors?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>In my youthfull daies, the moſt part of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of good will, the Seven wiſe Maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and there was not a godly Ballad that ſcap'd my hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſince?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>That good man Mr. <hi>Patience</hi> his works, and what elſe the Brethren publiſht.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>The Fathers of your Church you mean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Gent. as ſimply as look, my firſt Husband was a School-Maſter of great learning, and ſo given to his Scholarſhip, that a wud not ask me for a meſſe of broth but in Latine, and for modeſtie ſake (when a had a mind too't) wud wooe me to lie with him in Greek, or Hebrew. So that I was forc'd to learn my Accidence to underſtand him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>And did a not teach ye?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, the firſt thing a told me was, that a Noun Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive is the name of a thing — that may be ſeen, felt, and underſtood—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Admirable!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>And that a Noun Adjective could not ſtand — by it ſelf, but required another thing — to be join'd with it. And then a taught me to decline <hi>Lypides,</hi> and <hi>Hic, haec, hoc,</hi> Gen. <hi>whorum, harum, whorum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>And why not <hi>lapis?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe I will have it to want the ſingular number. But to proceed, I ſoon underſtood <hi>Propriae quae maribus.</hi> As for <hi>Quae Genus,</hi> I judg'd there was but little uſe to be made thereof.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52317:14"/>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Why what can a woman do with inſufficient <hi>Heteroclites?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Deficient you mean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis all one, Therefore I skipt over to <hi>As in praeſenti,</hi> which I ſoon got at my fingers ends.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Did you learn your figures?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I warrant ye: figures enough to make ye be in my debt as long as ye live.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I mean <hi>Syncope, Apocope, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not what you mean by ſtink-a-piſſe, or a pocky peece. I mean round O's for ſhillings, and half O's for teſters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you no better Arithmetick?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>I have learnt <hi>Multiplication,</hi> and the <hi>Rule of Three,</hi> I hope that's enough for a Woman. To conclude, my Husband taught me ſo exactly prick-ſong, that in a ſhort time I taught a many to play on the Band whore, uſing (after a compendious manuer) but three Notes, <hi>Large, Long,</hi> and <hi>Quaver.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I cud not have thought you ſo well qualified. But Landlady, a word in your ear — Can you help us to a pretty Wench. I'm in the braveſt humour —O I cud —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>What cud you do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>You may know his meaning by his gaping.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Whats that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Why a —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>If you talk thus, Ile not venture my ſelf in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany any longer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, what Sinner doſt a know from fifteen to forty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis pitty ſuch handſom Gent. as you are ſhud long ſtand in need of that which you complain for the want of. I muſt confeſſe I ſhud think it a ſin to denie either of you, upon that account, (you know my meaning) wert not a ſin to do't. As our Teacher Mr. <hi>Giggum</hi> has often hinted when a has ta'n the pains to hold forth at a private meeting.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>How now Landlady, what canting's this? pray let's have no more of hinting, and holding forth; they are not only word obſolete, but they favour likewiſe too much of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and treachery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope Sir, you are not angry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>No, not I, but gigging (as you ſay) you may uſe; it's a good ancient word, and ſtill in faſhion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>And holding forth in ſome ſenſe, is good too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52317:15"/>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, Gent. what ere you think of me now, I knew the time when brave Sparks would have been glad of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and would not have ſat down to dinner without me. Who then but Madam <hi>Pouch?</hi> ruffl'd every day in my ſilks, and wore Laces that coſt many a fair pound, I'm ſure; been Coach'd to this Tavern and to that, and in a frolick would have drank my Wine freely, God forgive me for't now. All my Neighbours did admire me. There was not any faſhion ſtirring but I wud ha't, what ere it coſt: and truly in every thing I was ſo neat —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>So it ſeems Landlady by your preſent dreſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I think 'tis now near the critical hour, when Mortals whet their knives on threſholds. What's for dinner? the edge of my ſtomack's as ſharp as a Turkiſh-Scymiter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly Sir, I have nothing but a Calfs-head and Bacon and a ſows'd Hogs Countenance; what think you of that Sirs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Well enough, but that the continual ſight thereof nauſeates my ſtomack. <hi>Hic</hi> with his Calfs head is always our firſt courſe, and not a diſh afterwards brought to the Table, but what is uſher'd in with a Sows Phiſnomy. Prepare ready what you have, and we'l be with you inſtantly,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall, and though our meat be homely, yet tis clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; pray do'nt ſtay too long.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! tis a prettie beaſt; the ſmile ſhe left behind her, with the court' fie ſhe dropt, has given me my dinner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſhe curvetted at every word ſhe ſpake!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>And her breech kils Musket ſhot.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Her eies wud inform an ingenuous Artiſt to propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the minutes of his Clock; for they are in continual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and keep time direct and retrograde.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>What a hand ſhe has! the true proportion of a ſhoulder of Mutton. As for her middle parts, (if they correſpond with the reſt) I ſhall look upon that man that duſt adventure to lie with her, as deſperate as Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> in ſhooting the Gulf. Let's in to Dinner.
<stage>(<hi>Exeunt.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 2. <hi>Scene</hi> 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Contriver, ſolus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>DUll Drones — a little pains might drein a bog, me-thinks — as eaſily as the Fens, and here's a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52317:15"/>great many. Ile about it preſently, left the <hi>amphibius Dutch</hi> prevent me. But how ſhall this be done? Thus —
<stage>(<hi>Enter Phantaſtick and Hic</hi>)</stage> the Bogs lie near the Mountains, which will afford me earth enough to dam'em up: but firſt Ile lay a foundation of hurdles, ſuch as <hi>Dublin</hi> is built on, to ſupport that Maſſe of Earth. So it ſhall be; tis as clear as a Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Demonſtration. The benefit that will redound hereby, will be triple. Firſt a vaſt quantity of unprofitable Acres made arable, next a diſcovery (it may be) of gold and ſilver Mines, which the barrenneſſe of the Mountains demonſtrate: and laſtly metamorphoſing a mountainous into a Champian Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. Here's the worſt on't, I ſhall looſe my name by't. The The King will confer on me little leſſe than the Title of Duke of <hi>Mountain,</hi> Earl of <hi>Monah,</hi> or Lord <hi>Drein-bog.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Surely <hi>Gog Magog</hi> ne'r talkt thus.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>A good reaſon why, he ne'r had that this fellow has.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What's that prithee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>A Maggot in's head as big as a Congre Eel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not think but a as ſwallow'd <hi>Euclids Elements.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>How do ye Mr. <hi>Contriver?</hi> are ye well?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, pray how do you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Never better; the Duke of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia</hi> lives not merrier than us; we eat, drink, and ſleep, without the leaſt care; for our hearts are ſo continually oil'd by good liquor, that they are antidoted againſt ſorrow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>For how long?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>The queſtion's groſſe, pray let the thought thereof trouble you as little as it does us: We'l ne'r want it while we have any thing, and when we ha't not, we'l try our credits and rack 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>And that's the way to crack 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo, as long as we have bold faces to back 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>To rime to that, I wiſh you ne'r may lack 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What, bold faces?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I mean your Credits; <hi>Phantaſtick,</hi> be rul'd by me, and Ile make thee a man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Why what doſt make on me now, an Aſſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I'me ſerious; the foundation of your well-being cannot be laid firm upon ſuch ſandy bottoms, as the tenure of your diſcourſe diſcovers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:52317:16"/>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>You talk like your ſelf, full of projects, and ne'r a won worth a blew bead: but what wudſt a have me to do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>This very day did I find in an old Map, <hi>O Braſeel</hi> with its height; that there is ſuch a place, is without doubt, and as report goes, very rich, and inhabited by very ignorant people: this I'd have thee do; let me have thy moneys to carry on the deſign, and ne'r fear, but this working pate will ſoon make a diſcovery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee good <hi>Solomon</hi> ſimple ſet thy heart at reſt, I have better things to employ my money about.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, think what you pleaſe of me, had I but money enough now, I've a hundred projects to encreaſe it by.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What an Aſſe art thou to trouble that contriving ſconce of thine with vain <hi>Chimeraes:</hi> had I ſo much money as thou ſpeakeſt of, I would tell thee how I would diſpoſe of it: firſt, my houſe ſhud be built by ſuch rare Architects; every one an <hi>Archimedes,</hi> (or a <hi>Sebaſtian Shyrley</hi> at leaſt), that the ſight thereof ſhud ſtrike the ſpectators into an amazement, or <hi>Gorgon</hi> like convert em into Statues: my Gardens and Walks there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhud be compoſed of nothing but pleaſure, in whoſe ſhady <hi>Meanders Venus</hi> ſhud have a thouſand Chappels of eaſe. But chiefly my Cellars ſhud be throug'd with all ſorts of rich Wine, and ſhud be free for all good fellows. My Larders repleniſht with Neats tongues, <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> hams, <hi>Potargo, Cavere, Olioes,</hi> and ſuch like; all for to reliſh our liquor: and then Jeſters, Muſitians, and exquiſite beaucies ſhud be our menial ſervants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>You wud permit me to be your Poet to compoſe Songs for your Muſick, and provoke your dul'd deſires by amorous Sonnets.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee do'nt interupt me: to be ſhort, whatever nature produces to be extremely delightfull, that wud I poſſeſs my ſelf of, neither wud I enjoy this alone excepting my Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Twas well you made that exception; for that ſtable that admits of all ſorts of horſes to litter in, now and then meets with a running Nag.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray on Sir, about your <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I wud keep open houſe for all roaring Blades, and one part of my paſtime ſhud be to make e'm drunk: the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſhud ride home in Coaches, and the ſervants follow after in wheelbarrows.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52317:16"/>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>Mad, ſtark mad. When you have obtain'd your wiſhes, will you not reſerve a place for me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>By all means, why thou ſhudſt be my contriving Cocks-comb, or my Fool, but that I fear thou haſt not wit enough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>I am bound to thank you Sir, but this diſcourſe ſuits not with my buſineſſe: you may pleaſe your ſelf for a while in your own fond conceits, and ſoon after ſee the folly of 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>See how the Maggot bites
<stage>(<hi>aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I ſee our purpoſes run in two ſeveral channels, therefore it will be needleſs to entertain any further diſcourſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Fare you well with your plots, let us mind our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.
<stage>(<hi>Exeunt</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Act 2. Scene 3.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewel, Bankrupt, Peregrine, Truſtall.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Gent. to ſay y'are welcome is no more than the cuſtom of our calling allows every man; yet I'le not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, what my houſe affords, freely call for. Firſt ſeat your ſelf, next what wine d'y<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> drink?</p>
                     <p>Boy (within, by and by Sir) <hi>enters.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>I think a glaſs of <hi>Canary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>There's your miſtake Sir, you'l find but little of that here, but for <hi>Sherry</hi> and <hi>Malago, London</hi> affords no better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>What you pleaſe then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Boy, draw a quart of Sack out of the ſixteenth Butt in the middle range.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I'me glad to hear you are ſo well ſtor'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo am I too: ſince I came to this City I could not command ſo many full bottles, as now I can Butts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>The caſe is well alter'd with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then ſhud we diſpare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſo, and now I live happy in the enjoyment of my Wife and an only Daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>How old Sir I pray.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>About eighteen, and though I ſay't, her wit, beauty and breeding contend for preheminence: you ſhall ſee her. Boy call hither <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                        <stage>(Enter <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:52317:17"/>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>This is a favour beyond expectation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>So that's well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Your pleaſure Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam excuſe my rudeneſs.
<stage>(<hi>Salutes her.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>My pleaſure is, that you go to your Mother — and d'ye hear — <stage>(<hi>whiſpers, and then goes.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay Madam, let me preſent my ſervice to you in a glaſs of wine,
<stage>(<hi>drinks</hi>)</stage> I cu'd wiſh the enjoyment of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany a little while, were the motion approv'd of by your fair ſelf, I queſtion not your Fathers allowance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir your pardon, my Fathers commands obliges me otherwiſe.
<stage>(<hi>Exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Ald. <hi>Thrivewel,</hi> I wonder at you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Why?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>That you are not infinitely proud.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>For what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Being the Father of ſuch an incomparable piece of beauty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>You flatter me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>I never was accuſtomed to't. O Love I never felt thy all-ſearching power til this minute.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, to all our friends in <hi>England.</hi>
                        <stage>(<hi>Drinks</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Enter <hi>Contriver</hi> projecting with himſelf.)</stage>
                  <p>Whoſe that? Mr. <hi>Contriver,</hi> y'are come very oportunely.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>So it ſeems.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, what news abroad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not, but I think e're long, the Inhabitants of this world, will all turn either fools, knaves, or mad-men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, what's the matter now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, I have been to have a bill accepted, and the man perſwades me, I forg'd it my ſelf; if it be not ſo, he's a knave to refuſe it; if it be ſo, then was I a very fool to do it ſo as he ſhould diſcover it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trive.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's the knave, and the fool, or the fool and the knave, but where's the mad-man?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phantaſtick,</hi> and <hi>Hic &amp; ubique.</hi> I came now from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading 'em from their diſtructive courſes, yet ſtill they hold, that they were born to no other end, than to enjoy pleaſure, &amp; they ſay ther's but one deadly ſin, and that's good husbandry; they talk of nothing, but Wine, Wenches, and Muſick, how to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52317:17"/>make men drunk, and to ſend 'em home in wheelbarrows, and ſuch like trumpery. And ſo I left 'em to come and ſpeak with you about ſome buſineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Alderman, for this courteſie I ſhall be better acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with your houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>And remain we your debtors.
<stage>(<hi>Exeunt.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis thus, I underſtand that there's juſt now arrived two Ships laden with french wine; if you make haſt you may have the firſt ſight of 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trive.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you good Sir, I'le go inſtantly.
<stage>(<hi>Exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>This plot of mine hath taken rarely well; this will occaſion his abſence for ſome conſiderable time, which wil give me a fair opportunity to court his Daughter <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                        <stage>(<hi>Exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 2. <hi>Scene</hi> 4.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Phantaſtick, Hic &amp; ubique</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Hopewel.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PHant.</speaker>
                     <p>S'life y'are too coy for a man of my temper, theſe long graces have too much of a phanatick reliſh. Come, you may gueſs at my meaning, few words among friends are beſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I hope Sir, you won't raviſh me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>By Heavens Lady, as long as I'me hear, he ſha'nt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure you, for I have more than ordinary reſpects for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Who you? why thou pittiful poor inconſiderable thing, made up of the parings of <hi>Priſcians</hi> nails, mingled with the excrements of <hi>Mars;</hi> doſt thou undertake to be her Champion, and doſt not deſerve to be her Foot-boy? I durſt ſwear the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſight of a drawn ſword, ſhall make thee run ſeven miles, without once looking behind thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I regard not thy cholerick expreſſions, but be confident thy over ſelf-conceitedneſs, (<hi>Narciſſus</hi> like) will haſten thy ruine. In any thing that may be termed good in thee, thy eies like drunkards ſee all double, and thy opinionative fancy, like a multiplying glaſs, makes a molehil ſeem a mountain: thus admiring thy ſelf, thou vainly doſt imagine, that every one that does but look on thee, does the like. Yet know I've as much intereſt here as thou.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray Gentlemen let not me be the ſubject of your quarrel; I equally reſpect you both, til my judgment ſhall be ballanc'd by him that loves me moſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then ſhee's mine by <hi>Priapus</hi>—Lady by all—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52317:18"/>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Who gave you leave to ſpeak firſt, ſhe freely confeſſes I have an equal ſhare with you in her affections.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>One as much as t'other, &amp; that's none at all
<stage>(<hi>aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>But Sir, as I'me your ſuperior many degrees, deſiſt from interrupting me, or I ſhall quickly ſend you to that place where you muſt be content to wait churliſh <hi>Charons</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for your paſſage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>If I can but keep my countenance now I ſhall have fine ſport between 'em.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, I make no queſtion but my ſervices have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you with the height of my love, and therefore what I now can ſay will be but a tautology. Y'are not ignorant that I am not only a Gentleman, but a Traveller too, and to ſhew you what quaint obſervations I have gathered abroad, I'le firſt repreſent to your view the common ſalutations of each Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Thus the neat French mode, thus the proud and ſtately Spaniſh, —(nay hold ſtill) or thus after the devouring Italian manner, I ſhall omit the ſlavering Dutch faſhion, as too clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh for my imitation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir your Prologue's too long.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Wud a were come to his Epilogue once.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>To pleaſe you Madam then I'le be ſhorter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>That's not the way to pleaſe her.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you love?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>As I'me a woman, I've a mixture of all paſſions in me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Then conſequently that of love, but commonly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens affections are grounded upon ſelf-intereſt: if they match with thoſe whoſe eſtates can't ſatisfie their ambition, 'tis to be ſuppoſed then, that there's ſomething extraordinary, that ſupplies that defect.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You ſpeak miſtically, I know not what you mean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>My meaning is not far from you, which time and your permiſſion may make you acquainted withall. Madam, my face is not ſo contemptible, as tempting, experience confirms my belief. I ne're yet in all the Countries I came ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, took the pains to court any, all contending who ſhould firſt proſtitute her ſelf to my pleaſure. I liv'd in <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> three months, where no Engliſh man before durſt venture; the Dukes only daughter taking notice of my ſuper-excellent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52317:18"/>qualifications, as likewiſe the exact ſimetrical proportion of my body, fell ſo deeply in love with me, that I was neceſſitated to ſatisfie her deſires, to ſave her life. And to ſave mine (the <hi>Duke</hi> being informed of what was done) there being no ſhipping in the harbour, I was fain to put to ſea in a Waſh-boal, and the only ſayl I had, was the fore part of my ſhirt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>A yard I grant him. But what did a do for want of a maſt.
<stage>(<hi>aſide</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>And by a ſtrange providence I Landed at <hi>Graves-end.</hi> The Court was ſuddenly inform'd of my arrival, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately was profer'd I know not what a year to keep 'em com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany only. I knew what they drove at, for they intended to make me the pattern to wear their cloaths by.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>But not how to keep 'em.
<stage>(<hi>aſide</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I cud have ſerv'd in ſtead of a jury of french Taylors, for the inventing of a new faſhion, as likewiſe they knew I cud teach 'em to ſpeak well, and redeem their Tongues from being penſioners to abſurd ſilence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I now plainly ſee you are a Travelles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>How handſomely the gives him the lye; but the fool (I believe) ha's not ſo much witt to apprehend it.
<stage>(<hi>aſide</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What you expreſs is nothing but truth. Nay more I durſt challenge the whole world to parallel my ſtrange obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>More ſtrange then true: but I'me glad a has travel'd ſo far from his ſubject.
<stage>(<hi>aſide</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le tell you one of 'em, I met with a fellow about a league from Pernaſſus, falling into diſcourſe (for a ſpake perfectly the Rabbinical, and I anſwer'd him in mank's) we at length concluded to deſcend the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid hill, and drink our mornings draught at Hellicon, having carrows'd ſo long that we began to be mellow, a ſpake to me in five ſeveral Languages at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I have heard of thoſe that have ſpoken their words by cluſters, but certainly the tother's impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52317:19"/>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>The Method that he obſerv'd therein will ſalve up all contradiction: for with his tongue a wud vowel out the lofty <hi>Italian,</hi> in the mean time the proud <hi>Spaniſh</hi> came glittering through the rolling of his ſparkling eies; his cheeks (being ſwel'd with Wind) blew out the bluſtering <hi>Dutch,</hi> a ſnuffled the <hi>French</hi> through his noſe; and the grumbling of his diſſatisfied belly (at the ſame time) ſpake articulately the <hi>Hungarian.</hi> I cud tell you of a thouſand more, which are now too tedious to relate, yet hereafter the relation of 'em will ſerve for pritty divertiſements between us by the fire ſide in a winter night. Therefore to conclude, if my Travel, Wit, Birth, Breeding, and a handſom Perſonage, will not invite you to embrace my motion, I know not what will: Conſider of theſe things ſeriouſly, and I ſhall ne'r fear that an <hi>Hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique</hi> can rob me of your affections.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir, your diſcourſe has been ſo prolix, that it will require a very conſiderable time to find out what you drive at. However, give me leave to hear you both.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>That's my Cue — Lady, give me leave to ſalute you after my faſhion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I've been troubled with too many of 'em already. yet for once, how is't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>After the <hi>Hic &amp; ubique</hi> manner thus— <stage>(<hi>kiſſes mouth, eies, &amp;c.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>But that's not as you ſaid, every where.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I know that, I've done as much as was civil, pray do you the reſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Such ſcurrilous diſcourſe renders you ridiculous, and reflects likewiſe upon me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, I ſhall then wave ſuch deviations, and render my ſelf in ſuch terms that may be ſuitable to the greatneſſe of my affections: Proſe is too low a ſtyle to expreſſe my ſelf in, therefore thus:
<q>
                           <lg>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Free and unſtain'd with baſe intent,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>My love to you I tender;</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>A heart not gloſs'd with complement,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>As free I do ſurrender.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Tis Love commands, then how can I</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>So great a God as this deny?</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52317:19"/>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Your Beauty, and thoſe better parts,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>your vertues (which ſurprize.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Where e're they ſhine on mortal hearts)</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Extinguiſht have mine Eyes.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And 'tis but juſt that I ſhud be,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Led by that power, that blinded me.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>I will not vow, proteſt, nor ſwear,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>nor cog, as others do:</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>But only ſay, my fayreſt dear,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>I live in bliſs, by loving you.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And ſooner may the Cyprian Dame,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Live chaſt, then I put out my flame.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Rivers their courſes back ſhall turn;</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>the roveling Orbe ſtand ſtill;</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And ſulphurous Aetna ceaſe to burn,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>before I change my will.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Then give me hope before I faint;</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>No Idol e'r had truer Saint.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>This is ſomething to the purpoſe, if they be your own.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Madam</hi> I'me no plageary, I ne're yet wanted words to Expreſs my mind, and therefore need not borrow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>But you can ſteal: how cudſt thou have the face to repeat theſe verſes (I being preſent) thou know'ſt I told thee, I made 'em five years ſince, for my firſt Miſtreſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Let not thy Impudent lying provoke me too far.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I ne're took the lye yet without ſatisfaction, therefore don't repeat it, leſt I make thee a companion for ſubterian ſpirits.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou hadſt beſt, if tha'ſt a minde to be hang'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What for killing an <hi>Elfe,</hi> or an <hi>Aſs?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I mean thou durſt as well be hang'd, as draw.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le try that.
<stage>(<hi>drawes</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay have at ye then.
<stage>(<hi>drawes</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Murder, Murder.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope,</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Help, Help.
<stage>(Enter <hi>Kiltory</hi> and <hi>Patrick.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>What, Draw upon a woman (cowardly villians)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52317:20"/>(<hi>draws</hi>) what your intent, tell me quickly, or this all-piercing ſtell ſhall ſet your bloods abroach.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, We came not to injure the Gentlewoman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir, They are both my ſervants, and 'tis Jelouſy that occaſions 'em to quarrel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Madam,</hi> I ſhud think ſuch poor ſpirited fellowes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not the honour of that title.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I thing ſo too, Sir, I was forc't to entertain 'em, becauſe I knew not how to be rid of 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Madam,</hi> I'le quickly do you that courteſie, and by ſo doing, I may pleaſure my ſelf; her beauty hath already cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated me;
<stage>(<hi>aſide</hi>)</stage> 
                        <hi>Villians,</hi> Expect not the honour to fall by my hands. <hi>Patrick</hi> go cut their throats.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>For <hi>fuat</hi> joy, to put the <hi>Kill</hi> upon my ſhelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Go ſirrah, or I'le cut your's (turns to Mrs. <hi>Hopewel</hi>)</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>O yea, for Chriſtis ſhake, make help for my ſhelf moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or elſe poor <hi>Kilpatrick</hi> will be made Kil upon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>To provoke cowards too much, is the way to make 'em deſperate. (<hi>Beats 'em of</hi>) ſirrah, did not you tell me you cud fight, upon that account I entertain'd you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes feat, at cuff, or skean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>None ſerves me but thoſe that durſt blow in a charged piſtol, and valew a ſword no more than a cudgel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
                     <p>See for this, by got a chree he wu'd put ſome lead in my belly but there was no ſharge powder upon the piſhtol, he did make intention to cut off my head, feat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Be gone, I ſhall talk with you ſome other time, <hi>Madam</hi> ſhu'd I ſay I love you, from this interview, you wu'd condemn me as raſh, but blame me not, if your beauty commands me, to be yours eternally. May I requeſt the great favour as to know your lodging.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>It deſerves not your knowledge: Your pardon Sir.
<stage>(<hi>Exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Follow her ſirrah, and ſee where ſhe houſes, and bring me word, at the three Tunns.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If ſhe diſdainful proves, then I'le give ore;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Tis but the ſecond, I will court no more.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Finis, Actus ſecundi.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52317:20"/>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act</hi> 3. <hi>Scene</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Contriver</hi> and <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>MAdam, I hope the fervency of my love will (in ſome meaſure) excuſe the boldneſs of my intruſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſince the time that I firſt ſaw you I have been extreamly impatient, and the force of my imagination was ſo ſtrong, as to make me conceit every minute of Delay to be a compleat day, till I had found out an opportunity to make you acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the reality of my affections.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>And pray Sir, what do you propoſe to your ſelf, now you have found it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall in part eaſe my ſelf of a great load of love that lies on my heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Sir, if that be all, disburthen your ſelf quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, charity commands me to give you my attention, if that will do you good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Very much, if you'l let my penetrating expreſſions ſinke into the hollow receſſes of your heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I can't promiſe you that; for I know not what you mean, every word you ſpeak to me is an Hieroglyphick, or ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign language, which will require an Interpreter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Then Madam I'le be my own, and unriddle that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem which ſeemingly puzzles you ſo much to underſtand; I love you, and that in ſo great a meaſure, that were the quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of all love contracted together, it could not exceed mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>I'me ſorry that you have ſhot your Arrows at the wrong mark, your hopes have miſtaken their lodging, and you have caſt Anchor in a bootleſs harbour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray don't ſay ſo, I have a ſtronger faith than to be mov'd with ſuch cuſtomary denials, which your politick ſex ſtill defends themſelves withal, when the forlorn hope of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection receives it's firſt incounter. Lady, you are fleſh &amp; blood, and can't be out-law'd from the Court of Love; &amp; though your beauty, birth, and education may advance the verge of your thoughts to a far higher fortune than my ſelf: Yet I queſtion not but the ſtrength &amp; conſtancy of my Love may ballance it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir your eagerneſs puts me in mind of a common ſaying that what is violent, is not permanent; every days experience informs us that hot love grows ſoon cold; yet what I ſpeak is but by hear-ſay; for as the tenderneſs of my years
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52317:21"/>may perſwade any that I am unacquainted with Love-affairs, the ſame argument may make you know, that I underſtand not your amorous diſcourſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>The many examples of younger matches, are enough to ſway down the ſubtil evaſions of your ſophiſtical arguments.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Ther's no contradicting you, for they ſay men have the art of perſwading women contrary to their own beliefs; though for my own part (I think) I am proof againſt it, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning my affections to be guided by my Parents will and pleaſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Were I but aſſur'd of your conſent, I am confident of your Fathers aſſent, and then there can be no <hi>remora</hi> or impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to our conjunction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Excuſe me Sir, the world is now grown very deceitful, therefore 'tis requiſite I adviſe with my ſelf, conſult you as you pleaſe with my Father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>The reſult of which (I hope) will tend to your laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contentment
<stage>(<hi>exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I never yet cud give a reaſon for Antipathy; as ſoon as I ſaw him, methought of all men living I lov'd him leaſt.
<stage>(Enter <hi>Jane</hi>)</stage> How now, what's the matter with you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>The matter Mrs. I believe I have matter enough in my hand for you, O the ſweeteſt Gentleman (I think in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) that ever lay by a womans ſide.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What, ar't mad, Wench?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and ſo w'ud you too, had you ſeen what I did.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What was that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell you the fineſt Gentleman—I warrant 'a has—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis no matter what a has, but what of him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>He gave me a Letter, and enjoin'd me to deliver it to your own hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>A Letter for mel ſure th'art miſtaken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you believe your own eies?
<stage>(<hi>delivers it</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe for that matchleſs piece of beauty, Mrs. <hi>Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra Thrivewel.</hi> 'Tis a fair title, I'le ſee if the contents corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond.
<stage>(<hi>reads.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>How well did nature in her plots contrive,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>A way to keep her own prerogative.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>By the ſweet Edicts of her ſubtil Law,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Pride quakes, and ſavage creatures ſtand in awe.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52317:21"/>
                           <l> 
                              <hi>Them Man commands, and makes their fury fall;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>But Woman (Natures wonder) conquers all.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I that have felt the tempers of each Zone,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And know most climates, better than my own;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cu'd never love, till your commanding Eies</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Shot ſchorching flames, and did my ſoul ſurprize.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I am your Captive, therefore muſt my fate,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Take life, or death, or from your love, or hate.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt affectionate ſervant <hi>PEREGRINE.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peregrine,</hi> who's that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Don't you remember the Gentleman that you were commending yeſterday?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou talkeſt at randome.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis the very ſame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſhud a love me? and yet why do I ask that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ſince I know not well why I love him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>For what elſe, but for a beautiful face? and let me tell you Mrs. you have one that's tempting enough; for ſo ſay moſt Gentlemen that come to our houſe; Oh! I have heard 'em wiſhing — you know what I mean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>You are too bold huzy, pray learn to be ſilent, and that at leaſt will make you ſeem wiſer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed Mrs. you wud not only ſeem ſo, but be really wiſer, if you wud reſolve to make better uſe of your time: had ſome as many ſweet-hearts as you, they'd make more haſt to underſtand, what a pretty pleaſant life they (that are married) do enjoy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Peace, thou talkeſt idely. I find an alteration in me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready;
<stage>(<hi>reads</hi>)</stage> ſure this paper contains magick, otherwiſe it could not perſwade me to love ſo ſuddenly: O my freedom I now begin to fear the loſs ou't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But let it go, to him I'le not refrain:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This ſingle loſs returns with double gain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>(<hi>Exeunt.</hi>)</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Act 3. Scene 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Phantaſtick</hi> and <hi>Hic &amp; ubique.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>HIc.</speaker>
                     <p>Were ever men thus bafled? how glad the ſtrumpet was to be rid on's?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Hang her, ſhee's like the reſt of her ſex, that value
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52317:22"/>men by the quantity of their moneys, and not their worth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Wud I had again what I've ſpent on her, twud be now very ſeaſonable to ſupply my empty pockets.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir! are you come to that? ne're wiſh for't, if you intend to thrive: don't you remember your old maxim?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee leave off your jeering, and lend me a crown.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then your money's all gone it ſeems.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes I may thank you for't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Nere thank me for the matter, but thank your ſelf; however ther's a crown, but make no practiſe of borrowing of mee, this is the laſt time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Now y' faith, if thou wilt, weel go to th' Tavern agen, and I'le ſpend it, I'me half drunk already, and ſo art thou.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>No not I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Then th'art mad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Why?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou'dſt ne're have lent me a crown elſe; I conceipt my ſelf now as rich as <hi>Craeſus.</hi> Here boy, fetch me a quart of ſack, a ſhort life and a ſweet, ther's nothing like it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Pox o'thoſe dull men, whoſe boſoms are fil'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With the doubts of their fortunes, and cares:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May be ſtarve in a Priſon, that feareth to yield</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In ſeaſons of plenty, his belly a ſhare.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let 'em ſtill live in ſcorn,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With their money and their corn;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till the terrour of ſin makes 'em free,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They are not companions for thee, nor for mee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>(Enter boy with Sack.)</stage>
                  <p>So well done, ſill a brimmer.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here's a health to all thoſe that will never be poor,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That conquer the frowns of their fates with their wine;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That will quaff, and carouſe, and never give o're,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till their faces by drinking like Comets do ſhine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In theſe we'l delight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>(<hi>Enter</hi> Pouch.)</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With theſe we'll unite,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And our happineſs ſtill ſhall endure,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As long as our company Sack can procure.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very well Gentlemen, that you are ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52317:22"/>but I'de have you remember, you did not diſcharge the large reckoning laſt night. I don't like this ſhuffling, you can run oth' ſcore in my houſe, and find ready money abroad for the Tavern. Gentlemen, I can ſtay no longer, my Brewer muſt be paid, and my Baker has been here to day for money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>As for your Brewer he may be an honeſt fellow; but hang your Baker, I have nothing to do with him: but pray what is it I'me engaged to you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su. Pouth.</speaker>
                     <p>Since you paid me laſt, 'tis juſt twenty five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings four pence. 'Twill be long enough before you Mr. <hi>Hic,</hi> will ask how much you owe, and if you did, I think 'tis much at one, for you never intend to pay, as far as I can ſee. I ne're ſaw a penny of your money yet, and that which is worſe, I know not when I ſhall: had I known you'd have roar'd and ranted ſo much, you ſhud have ſought your lodging ſome where elſe. Beſides, I doubt you have both been too familiar with my maid <hi>Dorothy;</hi> I examin'd her upon her crying out laſt night, and ſhe confeſt that you were both uncivil, and did — I'me aſham'd to tell what: wud I had been in her place, I de have taught you to have medled with a woman again after that manner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>And for ever after made us hate the cry of kitchin ſtuff for thy ſake. Prithee good butter-barrel, don't think to melt thy ſelf by our fire: thou Tun of Heydleberg, thy bung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole's ſo big that I am afraid to come near it, leſt falling there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I hazard a drowning. Had <hi>Garagantua</hi> liv'd, thou mightſt have taught him, without much endangering of him, to have kneaded dough in thy trough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Could a man have but ſeen 'em in conjunction, the reſemblance had been to nothing more proper than the Ox at St. <hi>James</hi>'s fair, roaſted whole with a Pudding in his belly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Come Landlady I have more charitable thoughts than to think thee a — becauſe thy age wants temptation; But I'me ſure not hot inclination; but as for cheating and extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (two excellent moral vertues) they've qualified thee for a ſhee-ſaint of thy profeſſion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>But that I am patient, and not given to the language of <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> I would ſay, that thou art a ſon of the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to abuſe an honeſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52317:23"/>woman of my ſort; thou ſpawn of Iniquity; vile, vain, Vilainous Raskal: 'Tis no wonder thou ſhould'ſt thus ſcoff at me, thy ſelf being ſo handſome, come up here, thou maggot fac't fellow; thy hoſe wu'd ſerve for a hand-ſaw; Get thee a lookinglaſs, and there thou ſhalt ſee the Image of <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> newly come from graſs, away, foh, thou ſtink'ſt of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, there's ſomething in thy face that bears the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of a prophane large wrought Chriſtmaſs candle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>This won't do, I muſt cog her into a better humour.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide</hi>)</stage> Honeſt <hi>Landlady,</hi> I was but in jeſt all this while, only to try your temper: to be ſerious, what you find fault withall, ſhall ſpeedily be amended, as for what I owe you, my bills of exchange, (which I expect by every poſt) are enough to ſatisfie you ten times over, and ſo here's to ye
<stage>(<hi>ſhe Drinks</hi>)</stage> nay y'faith Drink't off.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Come lets be merry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Boy call in the muſick I ſent for: my Land-Lady and I muſt have a Daunce.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>I can't Daunce, I'me old, but when I was yong I could have footed it to the horn-pipe, with the beſt of 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay then I durſt ſwear you han't forgot it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(<hi>They Dance.</hi>)</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Well done y'faith, y'ave been a notable laſs in your days I warrant you;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su. Pou.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not ſo old yet, but that I can have a young man
<stage>(<hi>or two for need</hi>)</stage> as handſome as either of you, no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Certainly he was born blind then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su. Pou.</speaker>
                     <p>But 'tis beſt to keep my ſelf as I am, and then I need not be in continual jealouſie of my maids, nor ſtay ſo long for my husbands coming home from the Tavern, that my meat is either rotten roaſted, or cold; ſit up till twelve a clock at night; If he comes home, then to be ſure hee's drunk, and falls a rayling at me: if not, ten to one he ha's taken up his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with one wench or other. No, no, ther's ne're a yong man of e'm all ſhall ſo delude me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I wonder who wu'd, unleſs it be one that is troubled with a continual foul ſtomach, and ſo to ſave charges wu'd make uſe of her face to give him a vomit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su. Pou.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Gentlemen, my buſineſs calls me away, pray
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52317:23"/>don't force me to riſe in my ſmock age'n, to let you in, when you are out late.
<stage>(<hi>Exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant, Hic,</speaker>
                     <p>Your Landlady won't alwayes thus be put off with fine words.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I know that, I ſee ther's but one way; my cloaks muſt lye by't I faith: and now I think on't, Alderman <hi>Thrivewel</hi> is a fit perſon for my purpoſe. 'Twere better they were Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned than I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>It's true, y'faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, when all is gone I'le not diſpair; for 'tis an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of my faith, I ſhall ne're want; how e're tis with you now, I believe I ſhall ſee you in the ſame condition e're it be long.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>If thou ſhu'dſt ſee me as poor as thy ſelf, yet there wilbe a great deal of difference between thee and me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee why?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe I have more wit and a better carriage than thou haſt to carry it off.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>O The impudence of folly! thoſe commonly which conceipt themſelves the wiſeſt, are oft found the veryeſt fooles. Doſt thou talk of witt, when thy ignorance has no ſimilitude, and thy carriage no compariſon. Thy fine cloathes like a cork boys thee above water, and thy ſmall remayning ſtock of money, like ballaſt, keepes ſteady the giddly veſſel of thy brain, which otherwiſe wu'd with every blaſt of misfortunes, be quite turned topſey turvey; neither haſt thou ſchollarſhip to ſollace thee in thy adverſity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>And what does thy learning avail thee, when thy Landlady calls for money? ſee then whether you can perſwade the ſerjeant, with your hard words, to let you go; I durſt ſay your quaint fancyes will hardly bayl you out of priſon; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will your learned Poems pay your fees. <hi>Hic,</hi> I'le give you good advice; never pawn your cloaks, as you intend, till you have tryed what you can take up upon your ſchollarſhip; thy cloak will ſerve to keep thee warm, and feed thee too for a while, when all the profound Authors thou haſt read, can't adviſe thee how to procure one meales meat; he that has money, commands every thing, with which I can obtain the opinion of being a witt too. Han't I known a rich young heir, been cry'd up for a witty perſon, when the Iliads of his diſcourſe, wu'd not afford a nutſhell of ſence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:52317:24"/>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Content your ſelfe with your money, whilſt you have it, in the mean time I ſhall learn to underſtand, that there is ſomething that ſatisfies without it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(<hi>Exeunt.</hi>)</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Act 3. Scene 3.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Bankrupt</hi> and <hi>Truſtal.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſtal.</speaker>
                     <p>PRithee, haſt a er'e a perpetual <hi>Almanack?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>What to do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I would be plac'd there, inſtead of a ſaint, an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fool.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Wherefore?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why that <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquitarian,</hi> and his antick comrade <hi>Phantaſtick,</hi> have lately borrowed monies of me: the one ſhun's me, as the <hi>Hare</hi> does the <hi>Gray-bound;</hi> the tother flatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies a ever receiv'd a penny of me, and becauſe he receivd it in private he bids me produce my witneſſes; and a third, when I askt him civily for my monies, he very uncivily threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to bang me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bankrupt.</speaker>
                     <p>His baſtinadoes wu'd have prov'd beneficial, had they broken the bones of too much truſting, and ſo well reduo'd again by a Jewiſh incredulous bone-ſetter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Now I ſee ſecond thoughts are beſt, by which I Judge thee one of <hi>Solomons</hi> fooles too, for had'ſt thou been wiſe, thou wouldſt have purchaſt thy name for breaking, for ſome vaſt ſum, and then 'twere no matter if the fee-ſimple of a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Bankrupt</hi> were intayl'd upon thee and thine heirs for ever.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>But what way d'ye reſolve on for a lively hood?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not, imployments being ſo difficult in their obtaining.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis true, though whole ſhips of fooles daily arriving vainly Imagin the contrary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Had I known ſo much before, the Indies ſhu'd ſooner have been my refuge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52317:24"/>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>What think'ſt thou of being a Rat-catcher?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee why?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, thy face does look like a Weezle, which you know is a great enemy to that ſoro of Vermine; ſo that thy appearance in a Houſe, hanted by 'em, will ſo terrify 'em, that thou mayeſt ſave the charge oll Compoſitions for their deſtruction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>No, 'twere better to turn Merchant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>But that will require a conſiderable ſum.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>There's your miſtake, for a box of ſneezing, a decay'd Tobacco-role, a dozen of clean Pipes, and a bottle of Strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, will make me one of indifferent good reputation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>O Excellent! Well, I'le be for the ſtudy of Phyſick: My Father being an Apothecary, 'twill facilitate my knowledge of Simples, and their Compoſitions. I ſhall want little but terms of Art, to puzle the Ignorant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Get acquainted with Barber-Surgeons then, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries, they help you to enough of ſuch Empty ſhells, that contein nothing: And be ſure let the excellency of your skill, chiefly conſiſt in the cure of the French Diſeaſe; I'le warrant you Patients enough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Don't you hear of the Armad<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Fire-ſhips abroad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>No.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>That's ſtrange, there's not a Frigot hardly, that either lyes moor'd up at Lazy-hill, Kilmainam, or <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he reſt of the Docks that properly belong to that Fleet, but they'r all ſoul in the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room: There's not one that ſayles from <hi>London,</hi> (let her be ever ſo well Rigg'd) but her Pump is choak't up, and ſhe opens in the Keel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>I've heard indeed; that your over-worne decayed, and unwholſom <hi>London</hi> Doxies, having no longer <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, nor credit there, repair hither, making it their <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ris, and paſſing for young freſh ſinners, are ſoon bought up as ſauce for Wood, cocks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Truſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Which your French Cooks don't alwaies compoſe of the wholſomeſt Materials: But 'tis no matter, if you may live rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably well, upon the unreaſonable, and all living of others.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I am reſolv'd upon't. Now muſt I put on a grave. Countenance, with a Habit ſuitable; Ranſack all Dictionaries for hard words, 'Tis no matter how little Intelligible, if amazing:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52317:25"/>Get ſome empty Glaſſes and Gally-pots, with Inſcriptions on 'em; And a Catalogue of Diſeaſes, fairly printed, all which at leaſt I'le pretend to cure; which done, I'le cauſe my Bills of an outlandiſh new come learned Doctor to be affixt to all corners of Streets, and not a piſſing place ſhall eſcape 'em.</p>
                     <p>Thus by this Plot, I'le change my low condition: A broken Tradeſ-man, makes a ſound Phyſician.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Finis Actus Tertii.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewell</hi> and <hi>Contriver.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you for your timely advertiſement; I hope the bargain will not prove improfitable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>May all than you take in hand proſper; but Sir, I have another buſineſſe to acquaint you withal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>What's that Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>The love I bear your Daughter, makes me humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to accept me for a Son.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>er of weight, and will require much ſerious conſideration. Have you made her acquainted with your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>With your pardon Sir, I ſhall confeſs I diſcover'd my never-dying love to her, but her anſwer thereto ſhe refer'd to your Diſpoſal. Neither is it my deſire to captivate any Maidens heart, till I am authorized by her Parents.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſpeak prudently. And truly Mr. <hi>Contriver,</hi> let me tell you, I ever had a good conceipt of you, and 'tis my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that you will thrive. The conſideration of which perſwades me to give you my conſent, and you ſhall have my authority to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand her. Boy—call it <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>Girle what think'ſt of a blusband?</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir If I may freely deliver my opinion, not as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>How's that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>They may fancy to themſelves pleaſure in the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52317:25"/>of that, the very thought of which is troubleſom to me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, you know not what a Husband is, till you have tryed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh I never may.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Away with this diſſimulation: Your Mother told me as much, when I woo'd her firſt, and yet, was never at reſt, till I was aſſur'd to her. Here's a Gentleman I reſpect, in whoſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (if you'l be obedient) I intend to make you happy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſtate I now enjoy (provided it ſuited with your will) is already more happy than alteration can make it. Good, Father pardon me. And Sir, for your affections, I thank you, yet deſerye 'em not in the leaſt; but I muſt beg your excuſe too, ſince in me I find no appetite to reliſh love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>It's a ſeeming piece of Injuſtice, not to retalliate love, for love, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>You are a fooliſh Girle, and know not what's good. Into what inconveniencies would you run your ſelves, were yee your own Carvers: 'Tis well therefore that you have careful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to provide what's beſt for you; I wonder what recompence can you make us for all our care, but by being dutiful and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; the neglect whereof renders you notoriouſly guilty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſan.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, Let me be diſowned for your Daughter, rather then be branded with that ſuperlative crime of Diſobedience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, well ſaid, now you ſay ſomthing, Mr. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver,</hi> let not any thing diſincourage you, for, her denyal onely proceeded from her modeſty: Let us leave her therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider on your Propoſals, and my Reſolutions: They can't but take deeply with her: But I muſt talk with you in private, about ſome thing that muſt be done before the Nuptials are celebrated.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit <hi>Thrivewell.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le follow you inſtantly. Madam, the utmoſt that I now can ſay, is but the ſame in effect of what I told you hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. In your preſence I can ſpeak in no other Dialect but that of love. I had juſt now come into my head—I muſt think on't another time—I hope your Fathers good counſil, with the conſideration of my tender affections, will (in a little time) work ſuch effects, that may ſatisfie the eagerneſſe of my deſires, the full content of your ſelf, to the compleat ſatisfaction of your Parents.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit <hi>Contriver.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Unhappy I that am thus in the very ſpring of my love,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52317:26"/>thwarted by unwelcome contradictions. I ſtand betwixt two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, the Duty I owe my Father on the one ſide, commanding me to love one, whom in all the World I love leaſt; On the other ſide, my own inclinations forces me to affect him, whoſe love I prefer before my own welfare! What ſhall I do? methinks Age ſhu'd conſider of others that are youthful, by themſelves that were ſo? <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the ſame condition. They had a time to love, and wu'd have thought it hard meaſure, ſhu'd the freedom of their funcies have been contradicted. I know not what to think of old Folks experience, which they continually inculcate into our memories, to perſwadeous not to love, without ſome palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advantage: <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> unto me are but dead precepts—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Peregrine.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregrine.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſhe: Be reſolute and be happy. Madam, my Meſſenger of love I queſtion not, but you have received, and ſhu'd infinitely rejoyce to hear you have made him welcome. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palſive ſprings of my affections brought me hither, to ſecond and confirm the contents of what I have writ. If I have offended, I deſire to be tryed by no other Jury then that of your charitable thoughts, and being Aſſaigned at Loves Bar, I now expect from your Tongue, (the Foreman) the verdict either of life, or death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the evidence as yet has not found the Indictment, therefore I might ſuſpend my Judgment in pronouncing you Guiltleſſe, but that I cannot but freely acquit you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peregr.</speaker>
                     <p>Then Lady, to your Ladiſhips will I pay my fees, (kiſſes) aſſure your ſell, I've wilt nothing, neither will I ſpeak anything, but what I am ready to ſeal with the pureſt of my blood. O that my thoughts were viſible. My heart's too little to contain the greatneſſe of my affections.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>I doubt your Words and Lines are all but tryals of a Maidens weakneſſe. Where are too too many of your Sex, that are too too prone to glory in their erecting Frophies over our too too much credulity. We Maids have tender hearts, and are apt to take notice of worth, eſpecially when we find it in conjunction with conſtancy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Cu'd you love that man heartily then, that wu'd love you conſtantly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>I think I cu'd, provided he were well ſtockt with virtue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:52317:26"/>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>That's not poſitive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>I both can and will then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then, By all the Powers above I am he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you caught me thus? but 'tis no matter, ſince I cu'd no longer hold: Then by all the Powers above and below, I am yours. But Sir, my Father has commanded me to love one <hi>Contriver,</hi> but aſſure your ſelf, he ſhall never injure your intereſt in me, 'tis poſſible he may hinder it a while.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>He to our conſtant loves ſhall adde no doubt;</p>
                     <p>His own unworthineſs will work him out.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Scen.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewell</hi> and <hi>Contriver.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>HEnceforth I ſhall beſtow on you the title of my Son.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>And from this moment I ſhall eſteem my ſelf moſt happy by being ſo in all dutiful reſpect.
<stage>Exit <hi>Thrivewell.</hi>
                        </stage> Umh— how happy are all my projects, gramercy good brains. I am now clearly of the belief, my Mothers imagination was ſtrongly fixt on <hi>Oliver</hi> or <hi>Mazerin,</hi> when ſhe conceiv'd me, or that ſhe long'd to eat five or ſix leaves of <hi>Machiavel</hi>'s politick Diſcourſes. When I was but a Boy I could have cheated all the Boyes in a whole School of their bread and butter, and have eaten it all afterwards: As for Calves and ſuch like humane Creatures, them I couzened at my pleaſure, by ſucking their Dams. Now ſince I write my ſelf Man, go thy way, when e're thou dyeſt, there's none will ſurvive to bring thy ingenious plots to perfection. <hi>Exit.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique</hi> with three Cloaks on his back, and Alderman <hi>Thrivewell.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. Alderman, you're the man I look't for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>What's your buſineſſe, Mr. <hi>Hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>In troth my buſineſſe now is not ſo much <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique,</hi> as for the preſent <hi>Hic,</hi> and that is to borrow a little mony of you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed you muſt excuſe me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I mean upon a Pawn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52317:27"/>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>A Pawn, now you ſay ſomething, and what is't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>My Cloaks?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Did not <hi>I</hi> alwayes perſwade you againſt your extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant courſes, and now you ſee what they have brought you to.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> pray Sir do me that courteſie, it is to ſtop my Landlady's mouth, who daily threatens me with impriſonment, and <hi>I</hi> know not how to avoid it, but by your lending me ſo much mony.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> ſhud think Sir that you are able to ſtop your Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladyes mouth without mony; However follow me, and I'le ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your Requeſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Scen.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Kiltory,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Hopewell</hi> and <hi>Pathrick.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>MAdam, you are ſo incredulous of the reality of my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that I know not which way to perſwade you, that I love, if the free ſurrender of my Eſtate will do it, it ſhall be done without any reſervation, that thereby you may know that I value not my ſelf or what I have proportionably to the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Deareſt ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>The freeneſs of your Proffer, makes me really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that your love is incapable of Admitting the leaſt Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. However I ſhall not give my ſelf up ſolely to your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, till by the conveyance of your Land over to me, I ſhall be more fully aſſured, that you love me not for what I have, but for what I am. I propound not this to cheat you, but that as it may be the touchſtone of your Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>If that be all, were the whole Univerſe at my command, I'de freely tender it to you to be diſpoſed by your Will; and what Loſſe wu'd it be to part with the world to one, in whom ten worlds of Excellencies and pleaſures are contein'd: the poſſeſſion of you (me thinks) is enough to recompence the loſſe of All, that the greateſt Potentates do Enjoy. Every minute of Delay ſeems to me an Age till I have fulfilled your requeſt. <hi>Pathrick</hi> fetch me a Scrivener preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>Scriboner, arra fuat de Devel; Scribner—my ſhelf make no meyning for Dat at all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>A Fellow that writes Bills and Bonds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52317:27"/>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>Bills and Ponds! feir De vaiter is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why a Clark then, thou Blockhead.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>Arra fuat de Tevil wilt dou do vid de Cleark?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>That, Goodman Raskal.
<stage>Kicks him.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>If I make tell ſo for him before, he will not come for me afterward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why thou Bog-trotting, Beetle-head, tell him, I have bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs for him then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>Arrah fuat de Devil muſt my ſhelf go make fecth for de Clark, to put ſheat upon my moyſter, and <hi>Pathrick</hi> himſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit. Pathrick.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Now Sir I ſee you love me, and I ſhall ever endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that my Affections run parallel with yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Pathrick</hi> and <hi>Scrivener.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>So, are you come, a word with you Sir, here's a Copy of my Eſtate preſently draw a conveyance to Mrs. <hi>Anne Hopewell</hi> and her Heirs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray Sir ſee that there be no fraud nor fallacy in it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Now I hope you are mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Stay Sir, you're too haſty, have Patience till the Scrivener has ingroſſed your Dictates.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you'l be mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>As freely as <hi>I</hi> can diſpoſe of my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>In the mean time let's take the Aire, this place is too little to contain the greatneſs of my Joy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique</hi> without a Cloak.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſhu'd <hi>I</hi> now cry out againſt the iniquity of the Gods, that they ſhu'd thus leave the diſpoſal of human affairs to the Guidance of partial Fortune, <hi>I</hi> cu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d weep (but that 'twu'd render me effeminate) when <hi>I</hi> think that <hi>I</hi> am wholly extracted, and that by the Chymiſtry of my Folly, brought to the very <hi>Mercury.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Three Cloaks and all ingag'd, O cruel Fate</l>
                     <l>That wu'd not leave me one, to Palliate</l>
                     <l>My weather-beaten Body, and incloſe</l>
                     <l>My naked ſides from my deriding Foes.</l>
                     <l>My Angry Hoſteſs, (heedleſs of the weather,</l>
                     <l>Grown far with foggy Ale, and bound together</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:52317:28"/>
                     <l> VVith the warm thongs of Fortune) has forgot</l>
                     <l>What cold and hunger is, and ſhe will not</l>
                     <l>Shake hands with Pity, holds it is injuſt</l>
                     <l>To liſten to the Arguments of Truſt:</l>
                     <l>Pay and you're welcom, when you have ſpent all,</l>
                     <l>Farewell good Fellowſhip, Comfort's but ſmall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Well, what's now to be done, <hi>I</hi> muſt conſider, whether Hanging or Drowning be beſt, or what Death with the greateſt eaſe, and quickeſt Expedition, will convey me ſafe to <hi>Charon</hi>'s Ferry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat: in the mean time, as for the thinneſs of my habit, that muſt be excus'd with the heat of my Conſtitution; as for Eating 'twill render the Body too corpulent, therefore Faſting will be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite: as for Drinking, Nature has provided enough every where of that, which will prevent hot Diſtempers; and for Sleeping <hi>I</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but I ſhall have time enough for that.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Phantaſtick.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What ha we got here? The embleme of Poverty, this is it to be a Poet; ſurely hee's ill-belov'd of the Muſes, that none of the Nine wu'd give him a Petticoat to make him a Cloak of, now is the time for me to make ſport with him; who do you belong to, Prince <hi>Prigg?</hi> han't you no part ith' <hi>Beggers Buſh</hi> to act? you you look as if you were conning ſomething of that Nature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly Sir, <hi>I</hi> was ſtudying the Art of Begging, becauſe ſome ſay 'tis very beneficial to them that can manage it aright.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>But thou want'ſt thy implements, as a Wooden Legg, Falſe Belly, a Forc't Eye, with the Art of making Old Sores, and ſuch like undiſcernible Cheats, that may procure Pity: as for thy Cloaths they will ſerve indifferently, a Month or two will reduce them into the Tatter-demallion faſhion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>To which adde four more to make up a half year, and his may be in the ſame Condition
<stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>What Country-man art?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, my Country is <hi>Hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me ſee—where does that Country lye? now <hi>I</hi> know; Juſt three Degrees, five minutes from the <hi>Equinoctial.</hi> And what's thy Name?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that thy Chriſten-name?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> know not whether <hi>I</hi> was ever chriſtned, if <hi>I</hi> was not, <hi>I</hi>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:52317:28"/>had much wrong done me by the Pariſh, for <hi>I</hi> am told, my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left me in a Church Porch for that purpoſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>where do'ſt lye?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique—Pauper ubique jacet.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you are no conſtant Lodger?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>No, not <hi>I.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>So <hi>I</hi> thought, thou look'ſt as if thou haſt not came a nap ſince thy creation. And where do'ſt dine to day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Non hic, ſed ubique.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>That's no where, and that's it makes thee look ſo like one of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s lean kine, <hi>I</hi> can hear hither thy belly grumbling out complaints againſt thy mouth. How doſt intend to live?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> know not how <hi>Hic, I</hi> think <hi>I</hi> ſhu'd do better <hi>alibi,</hi> the neighbouring Country to <hi>ubique.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Sir, <hi>I</hi> knew you all this while, and do pitty your miſerable condition. <hi>I</hi> ſee thou haſt no luck at contriving thriving Maxims.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>However, <hi>I</hi>'le not deſpair, when Fortune's at the loweſt ebb, 'twill flow again; my Engliſh money being now ſpent, I hope the worſt is paſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee what's the meaning of that thundring conjuring Sentence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>In Engliſh 'tis thus:
<q>
                           <l>He is no Souldier dyed in grayne,</l>
                           <l>That can't indure a ſhowre of rayne.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>But what mak'ſt a' here without a Cloak?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>A good reaſon why, they're all at pawn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>And what's become of the money?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>One half I ſpent, and 'tother I gave my Landlady; and yet ſhe's unſatisfied.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>For old acquaintance I'le lend thee a Cloak, but no money, for to tell thee the truth, mine's all gone too, though I ſet a good face on't; My Landlady, no longer ago then this morning, fir'd a whole broad ſide at me; for my part, what to do, I know not, unleſſe <hi>Wit without Money</hi> can aſſiſt me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:52317:29"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Scen.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Su Pouch,</hi> (Sola.)</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Su Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>LOdgers, quoth he, with a Pox, hang all ſuch poor Scabs, my ſheet's ſhall ne're entertain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſuch Vermine: But that which vexes me moſt of all, they bring in their Wenches under the borrowed names of Siſter, and Couſin, dancing all night like Faries, their night-rounds, and imitating the Nightingale, ſinging with a prick at their breaſt; and they ſo ſlobber them, nay before my own face— I know not what they have; I'me ſure I have been purpoſely familiar enough with 'em, (had they but eyes to ſee't) and have given 'em oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities—that any man that had guts in his brains, wu'd have laid hold on. A couple of Ninyhammers, that might have had my heart out of my belly (as one may ſay) had they but done— but what was reaſonable, I mean; but they have taken the wrong Sow by the ear— Here comes one of them;
<stage>Enter <hi>Hic.</hi>
                        </stage> Now will I try how this Fellow's neceſſity will work upon him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſweet loving Landlady, how is't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Never the better for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope you ſhall not be the worſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I ſhall, if I ſtay till your Bills of Exchange come over, that you ſo much talk of; can you pay me the reſidue of my money?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Not at preſent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Then will I deal with you no longer, ſince I find your comings in but ſhort. As I am an honeſt Woman I can't be ſo ſatisfied.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>What wu'd you have me do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Since you cannot pay me, give me good ſecurity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I am unacquainted here, and I have but one thing left me eſtimable, which I value ſo much, that I'me very loath to engage it, unleſſe great neceſſity force me to'r.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>And what's this fine thing I marvel, that you are ſo loath to pawn, ſome counterfeit Jewel, pretended to be given by ſome fond Gentlewoman or other.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>No I aſſure you, this is no counterfeit: but hap-hazard,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52317:29"/>will you venter to accept of it in lieu of that ſmall Debt I owe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>What is't? I'le not buy a Pig in a Poak.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha, I gueſt ſo much all this while; Is't not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that thou haſt had my Meat, Drink, and Lodging for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but thou'dſt have me too? No Mr. <hi>Hic,</hi> I'me meat for your betters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Landlady, I'me not in jeaſt; if you will, ſo? if not, ſo? you may ſay hereafter that you had an opportunity which can never be recall'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Ar't in earneſt then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes by my faith am I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Why this is it I aym'd at: Youth joyn'd with Age is like a Warming-pan to a bed in Winter.
<stage>aſide.</stage> But ſpeak ſeriouſly though, do you love me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I heartily.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>And will you be conſtant?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>While life endures.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>And when you are married, will you ne're Wench more, lye abroad at nights, come home drunk, and then throw the ſtools about, call me old Jade, and cry who the Devil brought us together, and it may be, beat me too?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Don't entertain ſuch hard thoughts of me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Wo'nt you upon every ſlight occaſion forſake my bed, and then you muſt be brib'd before you'l lye in't again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou'ſt half perſwaded me then. And will you keep me company at home, and be a good Husband?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then in the firſt place I forgive thee what thou oweſt me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>And in the next place lets ſeal the bargain.
<stage>Kiſſes her.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's money, go, and redeem what you have at pawn. <stage>She offers to go.</stage> And d'yee hear, pray remember you have ſeal'd the bargain; don't you go now and ſpend the money's. What a fine thing 'tis to have money, I might have ſlaid long enough for a Husband, but for that.
<stage>(<hi>aſide.</hi>) (Enter <hi>Phantaſtick.</hi>) [Exit <hi>Hic.</hi>
                        </stage> Your too late friend, your Cake's dough y' faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye mean?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:52317:30"/>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>I mean to be married.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Married, ha, ha, ha, to whom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Why to your Comerade: You might have been the man, had you not been an Aſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Me! I ſcorn thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Scorn me, ſcorn to be in my debt: Now will I ſtay no longer; I'le have my money's.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed you muſt ſtay till I have it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S. Pouch.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay me no ſtayings, I muſt and will have it: And ſo farewel. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Baſe worthleſſe man, whoſe fetter'd heart can cling, Onely for wealth, unto ſo foul a thing.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Finis Actus Quarti.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. 5. SCEN. I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Bankrupt</hi> like a Doctor, and <hi>Recipe</hi> his man.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>HAs no body yet inquired for the Phyſitian to day?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Recipe.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, one that look't a ſquint, that came to have his eyes ſet right: And an old Woman troubled with the Palſie; but they had neither A farthing of money, and ſo I ſent 'em a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, 'tis ominous to truſt handſel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>It's ſtrange no body elſe comes; were you careful in putting up the Bills?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Recipe.</speaker>
                     <p>There's ne're an Inne-door, nor Piſſing-place, but is chequer'd with 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>His Banner.</stage>
                  <p>There is lately come to Town an <hi>Italian</hi> Doctor, who (beſides his exquiſite knowledge in the occult Art of Phyſiognomy and Chyromancy) perfectly underſtands the Divine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of Aſtrology; and thereupon can give judgment ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good, or evil aſpects of the Planets: As for Example, Whether a Maid ſhall marry her intended Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52317:30"/>and can diſcover who are Maids and who are not, &amp;c. and who can calculate Nativities ſo truly, that he will tell the moſt remarkable paſſages of any one's life, either paſt, preſent, or to come; he likewiſe cures theſe diſeaſes under written,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Sciatica Vande poca.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Palfie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Impotency in <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>reſtoration</hi> of <hi>loſt Beauty</hi> in a <hi>Lady's complexion.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Draw <hi>Teeth;</hi> and take out <hi>Corns</hi> by the root, and yet put the Patient to no pain.</l>
                     <l>—<hi>Cum mille Aliis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But moſt eſpecially that almoſt (here) Epidemical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, the <hi>Ghonoraea,</hi> or <hi>Morbus Gallicus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>To be ſpoken with at the hours of Nine and Three.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Phantaſtick <hi>and reads the Banner.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>As I take it, you are the Doctor that cures theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank</speaker>
                     <p>I am Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt then, I ſhall requeſt your Secrecy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>It belongs to our Profeſſion. But what's your Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I've got a Clapp.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Of what continuance is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis eight dayes ſince I firſt diſcern'd the Pain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Then in eight dayes more you'l diſcern the Cure? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe,</hi> bring me hither two Papers, the one mark't with <hi>P.</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>C.</hi>
                        <stage>(<hi>He brings it.</hi>)</stage> Sir, take of each of theſe as much as will lye on a Groat, in half a Pint of the decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Guajacum,</hi> and <hi>Saſſaphras,</hi> for three mornings together, and 'twill divert the vehement pain in the <hi>Scrotum;</hi> that done, take of theſe reſtringent Pills, three or four, Morning and Evening.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you Sir, What will content you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall leave it to you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>Then know, I purchas'd my Diſeaſe at ſo dear a rate, that I have ſcarce money enough left to pay for the Cure. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there's ſomething as Earneſt.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52317:31"/>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>I knew him in another Condition; but commonly the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Prodigality concludes in miſery: thoſe that ſayl in Ships of Pleaſure, near minding the Sea-marks of Diſcretion, are oft ſuckt in, and ſwallowed up by the Quick-ſands of Delight, or are violently daſht againſt the Rocks of Luxury. See who's that Knocks at th' door.
<stage>(<hi>Knocks within.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Recip.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis a Maid that would ſpeak with you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Banck.</speaker>
                     <p>Let her in.
<stage>(Enter <hi>Jane.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Forſooth, Are you the Outlandiſh Doctor pray forſooth?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes forſooth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Then my Miſtreſſe has ſent me to ask you a Queſtion for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>What is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Whether you can tell Fortunes or no?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>I can reſolve all difficult Queſtions. But what is yours?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>My Miſtreſſe would fain know how long it will be before ſhe will be married: She has two Suiters, and ſhe would likewiſe underſtand which of 'um ſhu'd be her Husband.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Have Patience Sweetheart till <hi>I</hi> have conſulted with my Authors, and I'le inform you ſtreight. <hi>Recipe,</hi> reach me hither <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Ptolomey,</hi> and <hi>Argol.</hi> How filthily now ſhould <hi>I</hi> have been puzled, but that <hi>I</hi> underſtand how the Caſe ſtands between 'em,
<stage>(Aſide.) (Reads.)</stage> The Perſon whom your Miſtreſſe moſt affects is tall, and inclining to Black.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very true, that's Mr. <hi>Peregrine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>He is a Traveller, and a well-bred Gentleman, and <hi>I</hi> find contrary to her Fathers commands, ſhe has promiſed her ſelf to him, the other ſhe hates. Bid her chear up, for though her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intends to croſs her in her Election, yet a ſtrange providence ſhall prohibit him, and ſhe at length matcht to her Parents, and her own content.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>I tremble to hear him: for he that knows all this, ſurely knows that all is not right with me.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me ſee, by my Figure, I find <hi>Venus</hi> Lady of the Aſcendant, and Significatrix of your Miſtreſs, ſtrong and in an Angle; which argues, She's at her own diſpoſal, onely vitiated by the quartile Aſpect of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> our of the fourth Houſe, numa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Father: but he being detrimented by being in his Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate (and Occidental alſo) his deſign is fruſtrated; and beſides he is within two degrees of his Retrogradation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52317:31"/>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Redograbation quoth'a; wu'd I had ne're come at him, I fear 'a will raiſe the Devil by and by; for certainly hee's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>The Man ſhe loves not, is of a Middle ſtature, Brown hair, a Quick eye, and has a Roman noſe, and is ſignifi'd by <hi>Saturn,</hi> our of the eight houſe, in twenty four degrees, thirty nine mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of <hi>Leo,</hi> and very near a Trine with <hi>Venus;</hi> but is prevented by the haſty interpoſition of the Moon's body, ſhe being Anguler, Lady of the Tenth, in her own Houſe, and in Sextil with <hi>Sol,</hi> out of the Twelfth: which intimates, that your Miſtreſs ſhall in the very nick of time be delivered by a Woman from him ſhe cannot loye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>This will be welcom News to my Miſtreſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Her Husband that muſt be, is here ſignified by <hi>Mercury,</hi> in twenty one degrees, ſixteen minutes of <hi>Aries,</hi> ſwift in motion, having many Eſſential dignities, and is applyed to by the body of <hi>Venus;</hi> which Conjunction being in a fixt ſign, and not impeded by the ill Aſpect or Application of an Infortunate Planet, (but the inconſiderable quartile of <hi>Jupiter</hi>) it muſt needs be that they will be joyn'd ſpeedily.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>And will they live happily forſooth?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me ſee my Figure again: after this Conjunction, <hi>Venus</hi> haſtens to a Trine with <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who is Lord of the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heaven; here I find a ſpeedy reconciliation between her and her Father: beſides <hi>Pars fortunae</hi> is in Semiſextile to the cuſp of the Aſcendant, out of the ſecond, and ſtrengthened by being in the terms and exaltation of <hi>Jupiter.</hi> Every Significator is ſo full, that in ſpight of fate, they'l live happily. I cannot Erre ſince my Figure is ſo radical.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray you forſooth let me trouble you a little farther: there's a Friend of mine, not very well, and ſhe deſires that you wu'd caſt her Water.
<stage>(Gives him an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinal.)</stage> Oh how my Heart pants to hear what he will ſay, 'tis my own Water; for I would willingly know the certainty of that which I have ſuſpected on Juſt grounds this ſix weeks.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis Raggy—beſides there are many more apparent Symptoms. Maid, tell thy Friend, ſhee's with Child, and I find by a ſtrong Planetary Conjunction, that ſhe ſhall be deliver'd of Twinns.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Then am I twice undone. But Sir, this will be unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52317:32"/>News to her, for ſhe paſſes for a Maid, therefore if you cu'd help her in this Neceſſity, I'm confident ſhe wu'd well reward you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Wud'it thou 'a me be a Murderer?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>O no Sir, but ſhe got her Miſchance ſo lately, that it cannot yet be a living thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou talk'ſt according to thy Wiſdom: here take this Powder, and let her drink off a peny weight every Morning, for nine dayes, and it will do her buſineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you good Mr. Doctor, I'le bring you your fee preſently.
<stage>(<hi>Exit.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bank.</speaker>
                     <p>I think I've fitted her for a Quean, that which I gave her will prevent all her murdering Endeavours. 'Tis a pretty good beginning, Heaven continue.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Scen.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Mr. <hi>Hopewell,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Hopewell.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>As for what is paſt, I freely forgive thee, Th'art now as chaſt in my thoughts, as unſpotted Virginity it ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I hope my frequent tears have waſht me white a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and thy forgiveneſs has reſtor'd me to the good Opinion of my ſelf for the time to come; Ye Powers above, deprive me imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately of that Soul ye gave me, ſo ſoon as I ſhall wrong that duty I owe thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And let me not live, when <hi>I</hi> ſhall ceaſe to love thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>My Deareſt though <hi>I</hi> cu'd for ever content my ſelf to diſcourſe in this Dialect with thee, yet now an emergent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which you ſhall Know more fully hereafter, will hinder us, and require your ſilence and attention a while. Stand by, Here 'a comes.
<stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Kiltory, <hi>Scrivener with the Writings, and</hi> Pathrick.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>See here the performance of your Injunctions: but who's that Gentleman?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>A Kinſmans of mine, whoſe advice <hi>I</hi> took in this weighty affair. Alderman <hi>Thrivewell</hi> promis'd to be here too; and ſee hee's come in the nick.
<stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewell.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Save ye All: come Widow, are the Writings drawn?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:52317:32"/>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Here they are: and take notice that in theſe I make a free ſurrender of my whole Eſtate to the uſe of Mrs. <hi>Anne Hopewell.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Goods and Chattels?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>All, all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>Ub, ub, ub, boo! arrow moyſter, wilt tow give away all dine own tings, and leave noting upon me poor <hi>Kilpathrick:</hi> ſuate ſhall my wiſe <hi>Juane</hi> do for de Cow dat make de buuter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milk, and de bony clabber for dy child and my ſhelf, and de mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laghane, and de garraane baane, and de garrane dough, thou didſt make promiſe for me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah leave thy howling.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſhelf no howle, me make ſpeak for you: By St. <hi>Pathrick</hi> and St. <hi>Shone Batty,</hi> my ſhelf will make no ſervant for de.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, Sign, ſign:
<stage>Kiltory <hi>delivers the writings to Mrs.</hi> Hopewell</stage> So, ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Now Madam, I've done my part, there's nothing wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but the performance of yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Which I ſhall quickly do; according to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, I freely beſtow on you, all the right and title I have in my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>That's a guift greater then the riches of the <hi>Indie<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No ſuch matter Sir, 'tis none at all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>How's that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Can you give away another man's intereſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>No.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Then cannot I give away my ſelf: that man, ſhe Kinſman as I told you, has been my Maſter this ſeven years, and ſhall be all, till I am maſterd by death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Am I now in the Meridian of my wiſdom, thus cheated by Female ſubtilty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, I like thy wit Wench. Well, I have ſuch an other at home, a notable Girle at a pinch.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I give you much joy of your purchaſe Sir, fare you well.
<stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mrs. <hi>Hopewel.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Col. is this Debenture-land, or are you onely an Adventurer: if ſo, you may come in among the forty nine men.
<stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt Thrivewel</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hopewel.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>Shoole a crogh, manam a dioule, thou greiſie micheer, by my ſoulwation joy a chree, y told dee, de Engliſh vid put de ſheat pon efry podyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:52317:33"/>
                     <speaker>Kilt.</speaker>
                     <p>Woman was the firſt that ever took the Devils counſil, and firſt communicated it to man, to the ruine of both their terreſtrial happineſſe; and ſtill I ſee he makes uſe ſtill of that Sex, as his principle Inſtruments to perpetrate the moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous evils. Impudence is a hereditary vice in 'em, other wiſe how cu'd ſhe have look't me in the face, whilſt ſhe made me ſwallow her guilded Pills of diſſimulation; and ſo intended to kill, when ſhe did moſt pleaſingly ſmile; they are <hi>Baſilisks</hi> that deſtroy with their looks; <hi>Harpies</hi> that allure with their face, to murder with their talons; 'twas well ſhe had not cheated me out of my ſoul too.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Path.</speaker>
                     <p>May ſtarſing come to her ſheeks, ſtrepoh granach, and may her fader's ſhild make dye in de priſhon.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Scen.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Caſſandra</hi> and <hi>Jane.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>WEll <hi>Jane,</hi> what news have you brought me from the Conjurer?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Miſtris, believe me if there be a Divel in Hell, he's one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee why?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Why? he knows what every one does, and I think he knows their thoughts: He deſcrib'd Mr. <hi>Peregrine,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver,</hi> as perfectly as if he had ſeen 'em a hundred times; and he ſayes forſooth, that you ſhall ſpeedily have Mr. <hi>Peregrine;</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Contriver</hi>'s deſign of marrying you, ſhall be prevented by a woman: And then he fell a conjuring up of all the Devils in Hell I think; he was ſo well acquainted with 'em, that he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led 'em by their names; as <hi>Jupiter, Saturn,</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> and I know not what beſide.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>This news has reviv'd me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>O but Miſtris—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>What's the matter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>O I'me undone, I'me undone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, prithee why?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Im'e aſham'd to tell you forſooth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>However I ſuſpect what it is. I ever told you what your ramping on mens backs wu'd come to.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:52317:33"/>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas that did me no harm: But will you keep my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets forſooth?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>I will, what is't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>About ſix weeks ſince, <hi>Robin</hi> the drawer and I, after all the reſt were gone to bed, ſate up late by the fire ſide; <hi>Robin</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed has born me affections any time this twelve month's day; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a great deal of talk, he told me he wu'd marry me, and upon that he kiſt me, I think, a thouſand times, then I promis'd I wu'd have none but him: then again he fell a kiſſing, and hugging, and tumbling me, and—I'me ſure I was never well ſince; therefore to know what ail'd me, I carried my water to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and he told me, ſhe that made it was with child.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Is it ſo Huſwife, that you have made my Fathers houſe a Bawdy-houſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, good Miſtris, did you not promiſe me not to be angry?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Is it poſſible that <hi>Robin</hi>'s ſo gameſome, and you fond ſool ſo heedleſſe of your credit, well, you ſhall both walk for't, and then try whether wantonneſſe will maintain you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jane.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Miſtris forgive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Huzzy, the love I ever bore you makes me pitty your folly. I'le get a friend-ſhall ſawder up the crack of your honeſty; follow me.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Scen.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Phantastick,</hi> ſolus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phant.</speaker>
                     <p>WHy ſhu'd I raile at Fortune, calling her Whore, unconſtant Queane, and the like; when my own ſooliſh ſelf, is the ſole Author of my preſent miſery. Had I not been infatuated, I might eaſily have prognoſticated my fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condition, by the courſes I then took. I cannot ſtay at home, the diſtemper of my body maketh me every where reſtleſſe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther durſt I ſtir abroad, for fear of Arreſts. Oh inſupportable condition! from bad premiſes, I cu'd now draw a worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: Farewel fond Femal pleaſures, and welcome that Pilot that will ſtear me to the land of forgetfulneſs, where my weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten Veſſel may be ſafely moor'd up, from the tempeſtuous, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52317:34"/>ſwelling billows of all misfortunes; Oh—I'me right enough ſerv'd. Here comes one that will plague me worſe then the Pox it ſelf.
<stage>Enter <hi>Hic.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>How now <hi>Phantaſtick,</hi> what's the matter, thou canſt not ſteer aright; ſurely thou'ſt loſt thy Rutter: You muſt be firing ſo often, that I thought you'd blow out your Brich-pin. Surely thy touch-hole is very foul, for thou recoyleſt wickedly; let me ſee thee walk,—Bad, bad—I fear th'art paſt mending by a a Sereing, ſo that the utmoſt of thy expectation is e're long to be all at ſlitters. Well, I am ſorry that ſo good an Hackney ſhould ſo quickly be beaten of his ſpeed, and dry founder'd. You ſee how drinking and whoring makes you draw your legs after you; come, thou muſt be ſtew'd, elſe thou'lt ne're be wholeſom meat for the worms.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee <hi>Hic</hi> forbear; my folly is ſo lively delineated by my fancy, that I am tortur'd thereby, worſe than by the Diſeaſe, I now groan under. Yet this benefit Experience has beſtow'd upon me, to know, How meerly imaginary was that Recreation I ever aim'd at, and what miſerable effects enſue the enjoyment thereof.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot much condemn thee in thy juſt complaints; for they have made thee look like a—I know not what— A male Factor that has been hung up two or three years in Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets;— Why, thou art ham-ſhrunk, and broken-winded too. Don't thy bones ach pockily? ſtand farther off, thy breath is none of the ſweeteſt. I perceive 'tis come to a ſnuffing in the head, a pox on that dampiſh ayre thou breath'ſt in laſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>A dampiſh ayre indeed; but if thou wilt curſe it, let be ſome other way, for it has that already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me adviſe you to be very careful, that you blow your face tenderly, thy noſe will never indure it elſe. If I am not miſtaken 'tis already not ſo faſt, as it ſhu'd be; don't you obſerve it ſhake in the Hilts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>Never give over; now I ſee th'art cruel, thou terrifieſt me worſe then a ſalivation, or a clenſing loation.
<stage>He flings away from him.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo faſt; move eaſily, you are but tender: going ſo faſt may indanger the leaving of a League behind; thus much to be even with thee; and now for one that ſhall new vamp thee again.
<stage>Excunt.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:52317:34"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Scen.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Kiltory,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hopewell.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>SIr, My Conſcience, and that principle of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, that I have ever preſerved inviolated, will not permit me to be acceſſary to ſo ſoul an injury: Though you may have juſt cauſe to complain againſt the ſubtilty and fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent diſſimulation of a woman, (my wife) yet you ſhall not have the leaſt ſeeming ground againſt me. 'Tis true, what once was your's, is now lawfully (though not juſtly) my wives, and ſhall be your's again upon conſideration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Col. <hi>Kilt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What's that worthy Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Your Eſtate being two hundred pound <hi>per Annum,</hi> if you will lend me a years anuity (but conditionally that you ſhall ne're require it' again) till I ſhall freely confeſſe, that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement thereof hath made me fully able.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Col. <hi>Kilt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir, your extraordinary civility and honeſty deſerves far more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>'Tis only that ſum, and the aſſurance of your friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that I deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Col. <hi>Kilt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>This very act of yours, commands me to ſatisfie you in both.
<stage>Excunt.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. 5. Scen. 6.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Thrivewell, Contriver,</hi> and <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>COme, come, never bluſh Daughter, 'tis time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for that anon, when no body can ſee you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Faireſt Miſtris, 'twill not now be many hours before you'l both change your name, and condition too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſand.</speaker>
                     <p>Deareſt Father, are you then ſo cruel to wed me againſt my mind; certainly you cannot but have heard of the ill effects of forc'd Marriage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold your prating, 'tis now no time to talk of this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:52317:35"/>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. Alderman, I am come to informe you of that, which will be dangerous to conceal longer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Peregrine,</hi> I am glad to ſee you; but what i'st Sir, that we may ſpeedily prevent it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis only the preſerving your Daughter from being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd; by doing which, you'l likewiſe inveſt me with the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of my own.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye mean?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Mrs. <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> your Daughter, who is as firmly mine, as vows, proteſtations, and invocation of Heaven (voluntarily proceeding out of her mouth) can make her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>How, how?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very true Sir, and I'm confident ſhe's too virtuous to be guilty (willingly) of the breach of ſuch ſolemn Promiſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you do but flatter your ſelf, I cannot ſuſpect her to be ſo facile, as to beſtow her ſelf ſo lightly on one, that's here to day, and gone to morrow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray be you ſilent, you troubleſome contriving Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, unworthineſs in the abſtract—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Peregrine,</hi> I ſhu'd have been glad to have known your Intentions ſooner; therefore I ſhall deſire you to be ſilent too, for the Pretences are paſt taking effect.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Father you'l break my Heart if you ſay ſo, for I muſt confeſs, I promis'd no leſſe than that worthy Gentleman has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, as for my fault (if it may be accounted any) I humbly ask your pardon.
<stage>
                           <hi>(Mrs.</hi> Contriver <hi>knocks at door,) and Enters.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Who's there? Come in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Cont.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By your leave Gentlemen—Oh, are you here Sir! I heard of your Projects in <hi>England,</hi> which made me make the more haſt over, to prevent you from doing that, which wu'd undo me, that am your Wife, and her, that you intend to marry; and likewiſe ſave your ſelf from the Gallows.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>The Woman raves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Cont.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No Sir, I'm in my right wits, though the baſeneſs and unworthineſs of my Husband's carriage (that hangs down his Head like a Sheep-biter) were enough to diſtract any one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Is 'a your Husband then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Cont.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Yes (to my ſorrow) this five years.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:52317:35"/>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Goodneſs! now are the Predictions of that rare Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger come about: Oh thou Villain; that cu'dſt thus attempt to undo A harmleſſe Maid.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Cont.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray Lady, were you She that was deſign'd for his Bride?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ</speaker>
                     <p>So it ſeems, though againſt my will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Cont.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Oh thou monſter-treacherous Villain! but that thy Conſcience is ſear'd, it cu'd not but hinder thee from committing ſo foul a Crime, upon ſo fair a Perſon. Is't not enough that thou haſt trampled me under thy feet thus long, but muſt thou ſeek a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſubject to execute Injuries upon. Why don't you ſpeak, and be hang'd? now y'are dumb, (with a pox to ye;) but if you were alone with me, you'd find Tongue enough, and Hands too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Get out of my Doors diſſembling Monſter— O wicked Raskal—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. <hi>Cont.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>How juſt is Heaven! I ſee there's no ſhelter from Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vengeance, no reſuge from the All-ſeeing eye. Now I am betray'd to my own deſervings. Good Sir Pardon me, and Lady forget me for ever: Deareſt Wife, remember not the many Injuries I have done thee, but forgive me. Now will I pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe Repentance, and make it my daily ſtudy, how I may for the future live inoffenſively.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Cont.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I like this Recantation well, becauſe 'a never us'd it before.
<stage>(<hi>Aſide</hi>)</stage> Well, I'le forgive, and let me requeſt all here to do the like.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>We do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Loving Father, this Obſtacle being remov'd, <hi>I</hi> know none remaining, but that you may be pleas'd, to let me perform my Promiſe to my dear Friend <hi>Peregrine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>By permitting which, you'le render me moſt happy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Marriages are made in Heaven, and queſtionleſſe it was there decreed your Union; therefore my bleſſing on you both.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, in that Word you have compleated my Happyneſſe; and now Lady we are ariv'd at that Port, from whence I hope we ſhall never weigh Anchor more, nor never part, till ſummon'd by Death's pale-fac't Meſſenger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Hic &amp; Vbique, Su Pouch,</hi> Mr. and Mrs <hi>Hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> and <hi>Phantaſtick.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>How now Mr. <hi>Hic,</hi> what's the matter now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:52317:36"/>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>Matter enough, Matter—a—mony.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee, with whom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>With my honeſt Landlady here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thrive.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay then we'l make but one Dinner for two Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hic.</speaker>
                     <p>This is as heart can wiſh. <hi>Phantaſtick,</hi> yet for all thou laugh'ſt and jear'ſt at me in my neceſſity, I wu'd have ſo much pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty now of thee in thine, as to make thee my Tapſter, if thou canſt go in Stilts, for thy Legs will never carry thee up ſtairs and down. But Gallants,
<q>
                           <l>Come firſt to Church let's go, and then let's dine,</l>
                           <l>And ſpend our day in muſick, mirth, and wine:</l>
                           <l>We'le dance like skipping Fawns, and gladly ſing</l>
                           <l>Soft Epithalmes, whilſt Bells in Changes ring.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
                     <p>That being ended, we'le conſume the night In thoſe ſweet Paſtimes, that our Loves delight.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
